<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Usuries spright coniured: or A scholasticall determination of vsury by T.P. Doct. of Divinity, being moderator at the disputing thereof by certeine Bachelers of Divinitie and other learned preachers: with his answere to a treatise, written in defence of vsurie</title>
            <title>Usuries spright conjured: or A scholasticall determination of usury.</title>
            <author>Pie, Thomas, 1560-1610.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 184 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09633</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19901</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105929</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841654</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841654</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6252</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09633)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6252)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1328:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Usuries spright coniured: or A scholasticall determination of vsury by T.P. Doct. of Divinity, being moderator at the disputing thereof by certeine Bachelers of Divinitie and other learned preachers: with his answere to a treatise, written in defence of vsurie</title>
                  <title>Usuries spright conjured: or A scholasticall determination of usury.</title>
                  <author>Pie, Thomas, 1560-1610.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 92 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Melchisedech Bradvvood dwelling in the Little-Old-Bailie in Eliots Court,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>T.P. = Thomas Pie.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through, and some pages marked.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Interest --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Usury --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6252:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6252:1"/>
            <p>USURIES SPRIGHT CONIURED: OR A Scholaſticall Determination of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury by T.P. Doct. of Divinity,</hi> being Moderator at the diſputing <hi>thereof by certeine Bachelers</hi> of Divinitie and other <hi>learned Preachers:</hi> With his Anſwere to a Treatiſe, written <hi>in defence of Vſurie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BASIL, hom. adv. uſur. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Seene and allowed.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by MELCHISEDECH BRADVVOOD dwelling in the <hi>Little-Old-Bailie</hi> in <hi>Eliots Court.</hi> 1604.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6252:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6252:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, my ſingular good <hi>Lord, the Earle of Dorſet, L. high</hi> Treaſurer of <hi>England,</hi> Knight of the <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Order of the Garter, and of his</hi> Maieſties Honourable <hi>Priuy Councell.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here haue bene ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie excellent men in our Church, Right Honourable, that haue written excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding well againſt the common, but crying ſinne of Uſurie, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other (whom for Honors ſake I name) the Reuerend Praelate <hi>I. Iewel,</hi> L. Biſhop of <hi>Sarum;</hi> the moſt accompliſht Diuine, D. <hi>Humfrie,</hi> publike Reader of <hi>Oxford;</hi> and the ſage Counſellour and wiſe States-man, D.
<pb facs="tcp:6252:3"/>
               <hi>VVilſon,</hi> Secretarie to our Queene <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> of aeternall memorie. All whoſe learned diſcourſes, ſound reaſons, impregnable ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, godly admonitions, and ſeuere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minations, little prevailing with the deafe Uſurers; for that the ſame are over growen<note n="a" place="margin">Math. 13.</note> 
               <hi>and choked in their thornie hearts with the deceitfulneſſe of riches;</hi> that they could not yeeld their due and wiſhed fruite: it hath ſeemed good to ſome, other ſince them, to deale with Uſurie by courſe of Law and judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciarie proceeding. Whereupon at <hi>Oxford,</hi> Uſurie was<note n="b" place="margin">Potions concerning Uſury by <hi>G. Powell.</hi>
               </note> ſet upon and apprehended; at <hi>London,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Examination of Uſurie by M. <hi>Smith.</hi>
               </note> examined;<note n="d" place="margin">Arraignme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and conuicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Uſury by M. <hi>Moſſe.</hi>
               </note> arrained, and convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted at S. <hi>Edmondsburie:</hi> and laſtly at <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> executed and put to<note n="e" place="margin">The death of Uſury, prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge.</note> death, and yet notwithſtanding all this, Uſurie is as rife in this land, and as commonly and cruelly pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctized, as euer, I thinke, in any age before: as Iewiſhly, as when the Iewes were heere in their prime: as unmercifully, as when the curſed <hi>Caorſini,</hi> the Popes factors, by his holie countenance, were here in their pride. Which thing, (as I conceiued) could not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe be, after Uſuries death, but that his
<pb facs="tcp:6252:3"/>
ghoſt or ſpright did walke. Wherefore ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king my Bookes in hand, I thought good to conjure this ſpright: and therein haue gone ſo farre (as your L. may ſee in this ſhort diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe) that I haue made the ſpright to ſpeak, and to tell both his name and nature, who called him vp, and what makes him walke. But to bind the ſpright, or to laie him, <hi>Hic labor, hoc opus eſt:</hi> not unwoorthy the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of great <hi>Hercules,</hi> that could binde the three-headed <hi>Cerberus,</hi> &amp; ſhoot thorow the fell eagle which fed vpon <hi>Prometheus</hi> bowels; or the cunning of the great Miracle-maker and diuel-driuer, <hi>Gregorius Thaumaturgus,</hi> which could<note n="f" place="margin">Gregorius Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanae. Ingredere. Niſſ. meſus vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta. Caeſ. Bar. annal. tom. <hi>2.</hi> Anno. <hi>253.</hi> nu. <hi>137.</hi>
               </note> write the diuel himſelfe apaſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, and ſend him packing, whence and whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he pleaſed. Indeed, I finde and confeſſe, that it paſſeth my cunning and power, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the aid of ſome greater skill and abilitie. Wherefore, right Honorable, ſeeing Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God hath bleſſed you with great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vauncementes both of dignitie and honor, and alſo of autoritie and power in this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth; and that by your great office of high Treaſurer, you haue many imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb facs="tcp:6252:4"/>
and daily experience in the vertue, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> termes it) whereof Uſurie is a deadly enemie:<note place="margin">Ariſt. Eth. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> Idem. Polit. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> I make bolde to craue your Honorable helpe heerein, that you uſe the meanes of the great fauor, which God hath giuen you in the eies of our grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous King, of your high place and authoritie in the State, and of that eſtimation, which the whole land hath of your wiſedome, to the ſuppreſſing of this horrible ſinne, which like a fretting canker eates up and conſumes manie notable members, and great portions of this common-wealth: one part loſing or indaungering their goods and ſtate, and the other part their ſoules. As we haue had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold experience of your wiſedome in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging matters of great importance for the common good of us all: ſo if by your like care and prudence, this canker may be cured; undoubtedly the whole common-wealth wil receiue an exceeding great benefite by you, being freed from the burthen of Uſurie, whoſe nature is ſuch, that it is compared by the wiſe Philoſopher<note n="g" place="margin">Plutarch. lib. de non foene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand.</note> 
               <hi>Plutarke,</hi> to Vultures which gnaw the guttes out of a mans bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie;
<pb facs="tcp:6252:4"/>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Homer</hi> ſaide: by the expert antiquarie<note n="h" place="margin">Antiq lect. l. <hi>12.</hi> c. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Coelius Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundus,</hi> upon the experience of the poore old forlorne debtor<note n="i" place="margin">Liu. Dec. <hi>1.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> in <hi>Liuie,</hi> to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, which is contagious and infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and which creepeth from the goods to the body it ſelfe: by the excellent Ciuillian<note n="k" place="margin">Bald. conſ. <hi>440.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Baldus,</hi> to the worme <hi>Teredo,</hi> which hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth as ſoft as ſilke, but will bite thorow tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: by the autentique Canoniſt<note n="l" place="margin">Sext. decret.</note> 
               <hi>Gregorie</hi> the tenth, to a whirlpoole, becauſe it ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth up wealth and ſoules; by the noble and learned King<note n="m" place="margin">Lycoſth. apopht. tit. uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae.</note> 
               <hi>Alfonſus,</hi> to the <hi>Harpyes,</hi> which deuoured the needy <hi>Troians</hi> ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; by the ancient father S.<note n="n" place="margin">Chryſt. in Math. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chryſostome,</hi> to the ſerpent <hi>Aſpis,</hi> whoſe ſtinging caſteth a man into a pleaſant ſleepe &amp; ſo killeth him. God who is rich in grace, and of infinit glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, increaſe his graces upon you in this life, to the aduancement of his Church, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the common-wealth, &amp; reward them with eternall glory in the life to come, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Bexhil</hi> March 30. 1604.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips humble at commandement: <hi>TH. PIE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6252:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6252:5"/>
            <head>A SCHOLASTICALL determination of Uſurie <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the diſputing of that</hi> quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion by certeine learned Diuines.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Praemble to the Diſputants.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S you haue learnedlie diſputed this quaeſtion of Uſurie, &amp; debated it <hi>pro &amp; con,</hi> for the clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Trueth; ſo now let mee, lighting my candle at the fire ſtricken out of theſe flints, make an end of this Conference, drawing my ſpeech to three heads, in the firſt whereof I will ſhew what uſurie is; in the ſecond, prove it to be unlawfull; in the third, anſwer the arguments which are urged for the lawfulneſſe of it.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>1</hi> What Vſurie is, will best appeare by the Notation of the name, by the definition, and by the diuiſion.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:6252:6"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>1</hi> The Notation of the name.</head>
                  <p>VSurie hath his name of <hi>Uſura</hi> in Latine; but there is this difference betweene them, That <hi>Uſura</hi> in Latine is taken according to his proper and generall ſignification ſometime for the ſame that the maſculine<note n="a" place="margin">Non Marcel. de prop. ſerm. Si pon. in epig. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>uſus</hi> is; as<note n="b" place="margin">Plant. in Amphyl.</note> 
                     <hi>uſurámque ejus cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris coepit ſibi: hee tooke the uſe of her bodie.</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Cic. pro Sylla.</note> 
                     <hi>Lucíſne hanc uſuram eripere vis? wilt thou take away this uſe of the light?</hi> ſometime metonymically it ſignifieth the ſame which <hi>foenus</hi> in Latin doth, that is,<note n="d" place="margin">Quod princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pali mutuo acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. Si pont. in Plin. ep.</note> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is taken for a Principall lent. But uſurie in Engliſh is taken onely in this latter ſignification; and it importeth ſometime the action, which the Latines call <hi>Foeneratio,</hi> the Greekes<note n="e" place="margin">Ariſt. pol. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and ſometime <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. as,<note n="f" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to de leg. l. <hi>1.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Ariſt ibid.</note> 
                     <hi>he gathereth riches by uſurie.</hi> Sometime the effect or thing which commeth by that action, which the Greeks call <hi rend="sup">g</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines<note n="h" place="margin">Quaſi foetus, quia foetus est, pecuniae Varro l. <hi>3.</hi> de Lat. ſer. Pomp. fest. de propr. l. <hi>6.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>foenus,</hi> both termed of bearing or bringing fourth; becauſe it is the fruite, which the principall in his kind ingendereth or bringeth forth (whereof<note n="i" place="margin">Baſil. hom. adu. uſur.</note> 
                     <hi>Baſil</hi> ſpeaketh thus: <hi>they ſay that hares at one time together do</hi>
                     <note n="k" place="margin">Plutar. de non ſoene. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>litter, giue ſucke, and are with young: So to the uſurer money at one time is</hi>
                     <note n="l" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>put to uſury &amp; borne and breeding</hi>) as when we ſay: <hi>he payeth uſurie:</hi>
                     <note n="m" place="margin">Athan. l. <hi>3.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>I will giue thee nine oboles uſurie for a pound.</hi> This we call alſo by the generall word, <hi>the uſe:</hi> but moſt properly <hi>the lone.</hi> This thing in Hebrue is called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>tarbith,</hi> that is, increaſe and multiplication, becauſe the principall increaſeth it ſelfe and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth more in his kind: which commeth of <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:6252:6"/>
to multiplie, increaſe, or to be more in his kind; as the commaundement of Generation<note n="u" place="margin">Gen. 1.22.8.17.</note> 
                     <hi>increaſe and multiplie</hi> doth ſhew, and of the ſame the Chaldean Paraphraſt calleth it <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>ribbitha.</hi> So that the reaſon of the etymologie in the Latin <hi>foenus,</hi> the Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the Chaldaean <hi>ribbitha,</hi> and the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue <hi>tarbith</hi> is all one. And the Latin, Greeke, and Chaldaean, haue to thoſe their nownes <hi>verba</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>ſeu conjugata,</hi> verbes of the like ſignification ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify in the action, namely, <hi>foenerare,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in Puhel, to lend to uſurie: the paſſiues of the Latin &amp;<note n="o" place="margin">Eſpecially <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>: which yet Baſil attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to the money alſo.</note> Greeke become Deponentes, and are attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the taker upon uſurie, ſignifying to borow upon uſurie: but the paſſiue of the Chaldaean is attributed to the thing which is at uſurie, ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be lent to uſurie. But the Hebrues haue no verbe <hi>conjugatum</hi> to their nowne <hi>tarbith,</hi> to ſignifie that action, marry, they haue another name for uſurie, and for the increaſe comming for a thing lent, that is, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>neſhech:</hi> and to that they haue <hi>verbum</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <hi>conjugatum.</hi> For the verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in Hebrue is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſignifying two ſeverall and diſtinct things, or rather there are two ſeverall and diſtinct verbes written with thoſe ſame letters, yet differing one from another <hi>genere</hi> in kind: for in the conjugation <hi>Cal</hi> one <hi>Naſhach</hi> is an Actiue by kind, and by his ſyntaxis a<note n="p" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Theod. Gaz. l. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> tranſitiue perfect, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring an accuſatiue caſe of the ſufferer, and this ſignifieth to bite. The other <hi>Naſhach</hi> in the ſame conjugation <hi>Cal,</hi> is a<note n="q" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. ibid.</note> Newter abſolute, and that is ſpoken<note n="r" place="margin">Deut. 23.19.</note> 
                     <hi>de refoeneraticia;</hi> of the thing which is
<pb facs="tcp:6252:7"/>
at uſury: which we for want of a proper word muſt circumlocute; as the<note n="ſ" place="margin">In uſuram da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Tromel.</note> Latin &amp;<note n="t" place="margin">Taenori datur. Vantabl.</note> Greek Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters do, as thus; <hi>which goeth to uſurie:</hi> or <hi>is giuen, put, or lent to uſurie.</hi> Of which latter <hi>Naſhach</hi> there is made an Actiue in the conjugation <hi>Hiphil</hi> which by his <hi>Syntaxis</hi> is an<note n="u" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. which thou ſhalt lend. <hi>Sept.</hi> Yet <hi>Caſtel:</hi> ſaith <hi>foenere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur:</hi> and <hi>Baſil</hi> would haue ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thoſe Deponents Paſſiuely, as the Chaldean doth utter it.</note> Acquiſitive, requiring a Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive caſe of the ſufferer, and an Accuſative caſe of the thing, wherein the action lyeth; (which kind of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pound <hi>Syntaxis</hi> the<note n="y" place="margin">Theod. Gaza. l. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> Grammarians cal <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) and it is ſignifieth onely <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>foenerare,</hi> to uſurie a thing to one: or to lend one a thing to uſurie, and ſo likewiſe, the Noune <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>neſhech,</hi> which is <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugatum</hi> to it, ſignifieth onely Uſurie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>2</hi> The Definition.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note n="x" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>The action is thus defined: VSVRIE IS LEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DING VVITH GAINE FOR IT. The effect thus:<note n="z" place="margin">§. fiſcalibus. l. infraudem. § de jure fici. Aquin. <hi>2.2.</hi> q. <hi>78.</hi> Bernard. de cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra rei famil. Melancth. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin. Theolog. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Plutarch.</note> VSVRIE IS GAINE FOR LENDING ANIE THING.</p>
                  <div type="declaration">
                     <head>The Declaration of the Definition.</head>
                     <p>The <hi>Genus</hi> in the former Definition is LEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DING: which <hi>Moſes</hi> expreſſeth thus <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,<note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 22.21.</note> 
                        <hi>when thou lendeſt.</hi> In reſpect of the party, which ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it to uſe, and payeth for the uſe it is <hi>borrowing:</hi> which the Hebrues expreſſe with the ſame verbe, but in another Conjugation, namely <hi>Cal,</hi> as the former was in <hi>Hiphil:</hi> as in Greeke the lender is <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, and the borower <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Of this Genus the principall (as we call it, like as the Greekes call it <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, and as the Latines <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipale Mutuum,</hi> and in one word <hi>Caput</hi> and <hi>Sors</hi>) hath his name in Hebrue <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Halloah.</hi> Now
<pb facs="tcp:6252:7"/>
lending I call that, which the Latines call <hi>Mutua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, mutuating</hi> and the Greekes <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> in their proper ſignification (for ſometime <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> hath <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>for uſurie,</hi> omitted, and yet is uſed for lending upon uſury) which alſo the Hebrue <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> ſignifieth: and not that which the Latines call <hi>Commodatio Commodating:</hi> which we alſo through the penurie of our language, terme lending. And yet they may well haue one common name, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they concurre in one common qualitie, whereby they differ from all other kindes of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractes, viz. that in them the ſame thing, that is transferred and paſſed to another, is to be reſtored againe, but freely, as the Lawyers ſay:<note n="b" place="margin">Cauſ. <hi>13.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> c. Quod au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem in gloſſ.</note> 
                        <hi>There are two contractes, whoſe nature is to be free, Mutuating and Commodating.</hi> So then theſe
<list>
                           <item>two differ
<list>
                                 <item>from thoſe contracts, in which the thing tranſferred away is not to be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againe, whether it were tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<list>
                                       <item>freely; as giuing.</item>
                                       <item>for conſideration of
<list>
                                             <item>1 a price; as buying and ſelling.</item>
                                             <item>2 ſome other thing, differing in kind or goodneſſe; as exchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging.</item>
                                             <item>3 a fee; as Emphytenſis, or fee-farming.</item>
                                             <item>4 a moitie of an vncerteine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder at a time; as ſocietie: for in ſociety the venturer doth paſſe away the ſole property of the principall or ſtock: So that nothing remaine, nothing is to be reſtored; if any thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, euery partner is to haue his ſhare.</item>
                                             <item>5 ſome other gift &amp;c. as <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus innominati.</hi>
                                             </item>
                                          </list>
                                       </item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <pb facs="tcp:6252:8"/>from thoſe contractes, in which the ſame thing is to be reſtored a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, but the uſe was paſſed away for conſideration either of
<list>
                                       <item>hire; as letting of chattels.</item>
                                       <item>rent; as ſetting and farming out of land.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>one from another, becauſe the ſame thing which is tranſferred and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red away, is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in
<list>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>Indiuiduo;</hi> and that is<note n="c" place="margin">§ Commod.</note> commodating, becauſe the propertie of the thing was never paſſed away, but only the uſe of it: as I lend you my horſe to ride, to draw &amp;c. but you muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the ſame horſe againe. This co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modating if it be not free, but any thing taken for the uſe, is turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to letting and hiring; and<note n="d" place="margin">Exod. 22.</note> there the uſer ſtands to the hazzard,<note n="e" place="margin">L. <hi>2.</hi> § ſi certo petat.</note> heere the owner.</item>
                                       <item>
                                          <hi>Specie,</hi> onelie; and that is mutuating, becauſe the propertie of the thing <hi>(indiuidui)</hi> was cleane alienated to the borrower, that he might ſpend it by conſuming of it, or alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating of it at his pleaſure: otherwiſe there could not haue beene that uſe of it, which that kinde of contract requireth, which is to be ſpent; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſame thing in <hi>indiuiduo</hi> can not be reſtored againe being ſpent: but onely the ſame in <hi>ſpecie</hi> or quantitie, be it by number, waight, or meaſure.<note n="f" place="margin">L. <hi>2. §</hi> Appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lata. ff. de reb. era. Glanvil. l. <hi>10.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
                                          </note> For things onely which paſſe from man to man, by number, waight and meaſure, may be mutua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: and they are mutuated, when they be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to another to be ſpent, upon couenant to haue reſtored ſo much againe in <hi>eadem ſpecie,</hi> otherwiſe if thoſe verie things be lent to any uſe or end, ſo that the borrower ſpend them not, but reſtore the
<pb facs="tcp:6252:8"/>
ſame peeces againe; it is commodating, not mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating: as if I lend you ten faire Soueraignes to carie in your purſe for a ſhew, or to decoct them in a medicine for Phyſicke, it is commodating; for which uſe if I take any thing, it is letting and hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: but if I lend you the ſame ten Soueraignes to ſpend or lay out, it is mutuating, for which uſe, if I take any thing, it is uſurie. So this <hi>genus</hi> doth exclude from uſurie all other contracts, ſaue this kind of lending, which in Latine is termed <hi>Mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atio;</hi> and all gaine or profit ariſing from any of theſe other contracts.</item>
                                    </list>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="difference">
                     <head>The Differentia.</head>
                     <p>The <hi>Differentia</hi> in this Definition is GAINE, <hi>Lucrum, idest,</hi>
                        <note n="g" place="margin">Varro de ling. Lat. l. <hi>4.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>ſi amplius, quam ut exolverit, quanti eſſet coeptum: that is more, than to defray ſo much, as it began for,</hi> or,<note n="h" place="margin">Hier. in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zech. <hi>18.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>quicquid illud est ſi ab eo quod dederint, plus acceperint, whatſoeuer it be, if ouer that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered they receiue more,</hi> whether it be in money,<note n="k" place="margin">Incrementum pecuniae vel pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunia menſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile. Biel in ſent. l. <hi>4.</hi> d. <hi>15.</hi> q. <hi>11.</hi> art. <hi>1.</hi> a. Aquin. <hi>22.</hi> q. <hi>78.</hi> Ariſt. Eth. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> 
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> or money woorth: which may ſerue to<note n="k" place="margin">Prou. 28.8. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>. 2. Reg. 4.2.</note> increaſe our ſubſtance, wealth, or ſtate.</p>
                     <p>This Definition doth exclude from Uſurie theſe caſes.</p>
                     <p n="1">1 The demaunding, recouering, and receiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the principall, for that is not <hi>lucrum</hi> gaine, increaſe, or more than I laid out, and the not pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it is accounted ſinne in holy Scripture. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.21. therefore <hi>Helizaeus did helpe the widow to pay it with a miracle.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2 Expences about the paying, recouering, or receauing of the principall, as for carying or fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:6252:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the money, making of aſſurance, coſtes, and charges of ſute.<note n="l" place="margin">L. Mutuis. ff. pro ſocio in gloſſ.</note> 
                        <hi>For it is not gaine unleſſe the charges be deducted,</hi> and likewiſe charges about the thing pawned or morgaged for aſſurance of the principal, for<note n="m" place="margin">Bald ad Leg. <hi>6.</hi> de pign. &amp; hypoth.</note> 
                        <hi>that which the Creditor layeth out for or about the thing aſſured increaſeth the debt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3 Conſideration for the perill and daunger of hazzard for exchaunging money from place to place, as you would borrow for a time 100. pound of one in London, and give him 10. pound to tranſport it to <hi>Rome,</hi> and to abide the hazzard.</p>
                     <p n="4">4 Intereſt: for that is not for the lending, but for lawfull and due ſatisfaction, neither is it gaine.<note n="n" place="margin">Melancth dfien. Theolog.</note> Intereſt is a debt, which he oweth to the law of nature, who hath beene to another effectuall cauſe of damage, or hinderer of his lawfull gaine, the lawfulneſſe whereof is grounded upon the law of nature, <hi>that no man be enriched by anothers hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance:</hi> and the<note n="o" place="margin">Exod. 22 14.</note> Law of God, which provideth, that the lender be ſaved harmeleſſe from contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent damages: and the rule of the Apoſtle;<note n="p" place="margin">2. Cor. 8.13. reduced <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> 
                        <hi>not that other men ſhould be eaſed and you grieued.</hi> This Intereſt comming two<note n="q" place="margin">Ant. de But. inc. Salubriter. de uſuris.</note> waies;<note n="r" place="margin">Aquni. <hi>2.2.</hi> q. <hi>78</hi> art. <hi>2.</hi> in reſp. ad. <hi>1.</hi> extr. de ſide juſſ. c. Pervenit. &amp;c. Conſtituas.</note> either <hi>ex damno emergente, by loſſe ariſing:</hi> as when by miſſing my money at my day till which I lent it, I am dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by forfeting a leaſe, or a band, or a bargaine, &amp;c. or <hi>ex lucro ceſſante, by gaine ceaſing;</hi> as when by miſſing my money at my day, I am hindered of buying at the beſt hand, prouiſion for my houſe, wares for my trade, ſtocke for my land, &amp;c. Here the Cannoniſtes and Schoolemen require that
<pb facs="tcp:6252:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the money be detayned after the day<note n="ſ" place="margin">Innoc. ext. de uſuris c. finali Iohan. Cald. ibidem. Iohan. An. ibidem.</note> againſt the lenders will. For if he lend it upon allowance for the gaine, that he is like to forgoe, it is uſurie. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that the gaine hindred were<note n="t" place="margin">In actu aut quaſi in act. Aquin. <hi>2.2.</hi> q. <hi>62.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>in eſſe,</hi> or as good as <hi>in eſſe,</hi> the lender being in a good way to haue it, nothing wanting but that.</p>
                     <p n="5">5<note n="u" place="margin">Extr. de Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monia c. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectus.</note> Redeeming my owne hinderance, for there I haue no gaine or increaſe, but only ſaue my own, which may goe with the Principall. As I haue bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gained with a Carpenter to build me a houſe for 10. pounds, which I haue paid him all or part <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>manibus:</hi> now he will not finiſh the worke vnleſſe I lend him 5. pounds more for a yeere: So I lend him 5. pounds upon this covenaunt, that he finiſh his worke by his time. Here is a conſideration, without which I would not have lent it him: but it is not gaine, nor more than my owne. Or I lend a Magiſtrate money not to put me to a fine, which is in his choice to doe or not to doe.</p>
                     <p n="6">6 The taking of a Penaltie for non payment at a time couenanted: for that is not for the mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating or lending, but for a default made in brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of covenant. For it is lawful to take<note n="x" place="margin">Prou. 20.16. Deut. 24.10.</note> aſſurance for a mans owne, and to be ſaued harmeleſſe, as well in mutuating as in other contractes, and that not onely by pawne, pledge, ſuertie, &amp;c. but alſo by penaltie of forfeiting ſomething for default: as for non payment of rent, to forfet the leaſe, or to double the rent, or to pay ten pounds <hi>nomine poenae:</hi> ſo to forfeit ten ſhillings for not reſtoring my hired or borowed horſe ſuch a day: or I ſell you my horſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6252:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
for ten pounds to be payd at Midſummer vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty, that if you deceiue me, you forfeit 10 pounds more. The reaſon and ground of the equitie of Penalties is,<note n="y" place="margin">Innoc. extr. de poenis c. ſuam.</note> 
                        <hi>Quia intereſt Reipublicae pacta ſervari, Jt ſtandes the Common-wealth upon to have Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants kept.</hi> For as<note n="z" place="margin">Cic. off. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Tullie</hi> ſaid truely; <hi>Nec vlla res vehementius rempublicam conſervat, quàm fides: There is not any thing that holdeth the Common-wealth together more ſtrongly then faith</hi> in kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping promiſes and covenants,<note n="*" place="margin">Liu. dec. <hi>1.</hi> l. <hi>6.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>cum qua omnis hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana ſocietas tollitur: together with the which all humane ſocietie is overthrowen:</hi> and therefore the breaking and violating thereof, muſt needes bee a great offence, woorthy to be puniſhed with due penaltie. Now there may be great oppreſſion in this, as in other contractes; as I take 100. pounds fine for a leaſe of 21. yeeres, reſerving ten pounds rent, upon a covenant of reentrie. In the firſt pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Leaſee defaulteth; I reenter: as this is hard dealing, and <hi>ſumma injuria,</hi> ariſing from the extremitie of <hi>ſummum jus:</hi> ſo is it, if the lender take the forfeiture, being nothing damnified by the default; but it is not direct Uſurie. Therefore theſe Penalties muſt be ſquared, by the ſame rule of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, by which all other contracts ought to be: as,<note n="b" place="margin">Luk. 6.31.</note> 
                        <hi>As you would that men ſhould doe to you; ſo doe ye to them likewiſe:</hi> and,<note n="c" place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.6.</note> 
                        <hi>That no man oppreſſe or defraud his brother in any matter.</hi> And the<note n="d" place="margin">C l. <hi>4.</hi> tit. <hi>32.</hi> de uſuris. L. <hi>15.</hi> cum allegas.</note> Civill law cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a heavie hand againſt the taking of a penaltie for non payment of money lent at the day, and condemneth it, as ſavouring of Uſurie, and<note n="e" place="margin">Bald. ibid.</note> 
                        <hi>ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6252:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to be put into the contract for the uſurie:</hi> and,<note n="f" place="margin">Salycet. ibid.</note> 
                        <hi>therefore ſo much as it exceedeth the lawfull rate it holdeth not.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>3</hi> The diuiſion of Vſurie.</head>
                  <p>This gaine or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ether
<list>
                        <item>directly, which is plaine uſurie, and here the gaine is either
<list>
                              <item>compacted by both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that is the<note n="f" place="margin">Uſurarius.</note> Uſurer and the<note n="g" place="margin">Uſuarius.</note> uſer agreeing upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome certain gain. Which kinde the holy Ghoſt expreſſeth thus: <gap reason="foreign">
                                    <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                                 </gap>
                                 <note n="h" place="margin">Levit. 25.37.</note> 
                                 <hi>to giue upon uſurie and lone.</hi> Which ſuppoſeth a contract of the giuer and taker, and this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact is either
<list>
                                    <item>Bare upon the uſers own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</item>
                                    <item>Secured upon aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of bill, bonde, ſuretie, pawne, &amp;c.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>Exacted by the Vſurer after the len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and this untill the time it be exacted, is vncertaine: for the uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer requireth what he liſt, and the uſer at his requiring, or for feare of farther diſpleaſure, doth yeeld it: as the neceſſitie of them which want<note n="i" place="margin">
                                    <gap reason="foreign">
                                       <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                                    </gap>; Baſil. hom. adu. uſur.</note> maketh them to undergoe manie things readily, which are indeed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their wils. This kinde is ſaide <gap reason="foreign">
                                    <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                                 </gap>
                                 <note n="k" place="margin">Exod. 22.25.</note> 
                                 <hi>to impoſe, or to put upon.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>Offred by the uſer voluntarily of his meere motion: either hoping the rather to borrow againe, or doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing leſt otherwiſe the lender will
<pb facs="tcp:6252:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
not take it well; or upon ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ground: but it is principally for the lending of that thing, and otherwiſe it had not beene offered. This ſome terme <hi>foenus liberale:</hi> the holie Ghoſt calleth it <gap reason="foreign">
                                    <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                                 </gap>
                                 <note n="m" place="margin">Levit. 25.36.</note> 
                                 <hi>to receiue uſurie and loue.</hi> Yet for the benefit of mutua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or lending, and the commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie obtained by it, it is lawfull for a man to ſhew himſelfe gratefull, <hi>&amp; reddere antidora:</hi> but yet in the ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der difference betweene uſurie and gratitude, men need to be carefull and curious, as going betweene the barke and the tree, leſt their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience before God bee defiled thereby.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>Indirectly, which is cloaked uſurie; our law termeth it ſhifts of ſale &amp; cheviſance: for the gain in outward ſhew is made ſeene to be taken for ſome lawfull contract; which contract is made the cloake to hide the uſurie. Theſe cloakes and ſhifts are<note n="n" place="margin">Eraſ. in Pſal. <hi>14.</hi>
                           </note> infinite: for uſurie is cloaked almoſt under every lawfull contract, the gaine ſeeming to be gotten by them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as indeed it is giuen for the very lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. I will ſhew examples of theſe contracts, which are moſt abuſed heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. uſurie is cloaked ſometime under</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb facs="tcp:6252:11"/>1 Selling; as I will lend you 100. pounds for a yeere, if you will give me for this horſe 12. pounds being worth 2. pounds: ſo the 10. pounds ſeemeth to be given for the price of the horſe; but it is for the uſe of the money.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Setting to farme; as I will lend you an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pounds a yere, but you muſt let me that farme for two pounds, being worth well twelue pounds, or giue mee twelue pounds for this farme, being worth but two pounds.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Hiring out; as I let you haue three pounds to buy a Cow, paying me at the yeeres end, three pounds for the Cow, and a noble for the hire. Or I let you a Farme, with a ſtocke of twentie kine up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, prized at an hundred marks for ſeuen yeeres, to pay the rent of the Farme, and twentie nobles a yeere for the hire of my Kine, and at the end of the yeeres to deliver me twentie as good Kine, or an hundred markes in money.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Free mutuating; as I haue not an hundred pounds in coyne to lend you, but I will lend you an hundred pounds in wares for a yere, and deliver you wares not worth ninetie pounds, and perhaps deliver a Broker ninetie pounds to giue you, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue my wares againe. Or, I lend you an hundred pounds in ſuch coyne as I have, and deliver you light gold, not worth ninetie pounds.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 Exchanging; as I lend you an 100. pounds in ſilver a moneth, ſo that you repay mee in ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes, ſuppoſing them to be worth ten ſhillings and ſixe pence. <hi>Howe Vſurie is cloaked under ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6252:12"/>
by billes, ſee notably diſcouered at large by Doct. Wilſon. fol.</hi> 116. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6 Societie;<note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Aquin.</hi> 2.2. <hi>q.</hi> 786.</note> In which as one may put in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney or ſtocke to make a Principal, and another in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie; ſo theſe three muſt be common, the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall, the gaines, the loſſe; and the remainder to be divided according to every ones moitie in the Principall,<note n="b" place="margin">L. Praepoſita. ff. proſocio.</note> 
                     <hi>ex arbario boni viri.</hi> Here if I deliver money or ſtocke to have part of the gaines,<note n="c" place="margin">Bald ff. pro ſocio. L. Mutais <hi>13.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> ſi foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerareris, &amp;c. plaerique.</note> ſo that the Principall be ſaued me:<note n="d" place="margin">Ang. de Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract. de ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate.</note> or venturing but equally take two parts of the gaine; or put out cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell,<note n="e" place="margin">Monald. in ſum.</note> covenanting to have as much as my Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall was worth, before diviſion, &amp;c. it is uſurie.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 <hi>Nomine poenae;</hi> as one giueth me an hundreth pounds to be payd by another, providing that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry yere it be detained, I be<note n="*" place="margin">Bald. L. Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca.</note> paid ten pounds. Or, I lend an hundreth pound upon a bonde of two hundreth pounds, the bond is forfeited, I take ten pounds <hi>nomine poenae,</hi> &amp; renue his bond, being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing damaged, or not ſo much, by his non pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p n="8">8 Intereſt; when I take gaine under pretence of loſſe ſuſtained by miſſing my money at my day; having indeed ſuſtained none, and perhaps let him keepe the Principall ſtill. <hi>Therefore it is good adviſe which one giveth, that the damage be ceſſed by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, to auoid both the cunning &amp; colour of uſurie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9<note n="*" place="margin">Col. <hi>6.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> de his quaefoenae nomine.</note> Pawne; as I lend money upon a pawne, and make profit or commoditie by the pawne.</p>
                  <p n="10">10<note n="a" place="margin">Prov. Lindw. l. <hi>3.</hi> de vigori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, c. unico. Extra. de pign. c. illo vos Extr. de uſur. c. <hi>1. 2.</hi> &amp; ult. <hi>13.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> c. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</note> Morgage; as you bind your land woorth ten pounds a yeere to me for lending you an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6252:12"/>
pounds. In this caſe and the former, often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times there is a plaine ſale made of the thing, with a <hi>Proviſo retrovèndendi,</hi> that the ſeller may redeeme it againe, which is a lawfull contract: as appeareth <hi>Levit.</hi> 25. But hereif there be more to be repaied, then was laid downe for it,<note n="b" place="margin">Monald. in ſumm.</note> it is uſurie. As I mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage land, or pawne plate to you for an hundreth pounds, with a bill of ſale, providing that within a yeere, I may redeeme it for an 110. pounds, or if the borower retaine libertie to himſelfe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand his money againe. And though the ſame price be to be repaied, yet if the ſeller ſtand char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with it, it is uſurie,<note n="c" place="margin">ff. de periculo &amp; con. reivend. L. id quod.</note> becauſe it is againſt the nature of ſelling. Moreouer the opinion of<note n="d" place="margin">Host. in c. Ad noſtram de empt. &amp; vendit. Ext. de pignor. c. Illo vos. Panorm. conſ. <hi>76.</hi> Ioh. de Imo. in c. ad noſtram de empt. &amp; vendit. Et multi alij.</note> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Lawyers is, that if there concurre with the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant <hi>retrovendendi</hi> another conjecture or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, it is uſurie: as, if the price be under the value, or the buyer a knowen Uſurer, or hath ſold his owne land as commodious as that, to make this contract, or it appeare, that the ſeller had no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of ſelling. But the<note n="e" place="margin">Ang. L. <hi>2.</hi> C. de pac. inter emp &amp; vend. Monal. in ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. Alexan. de Hales p. <hi>3.</hi> de praec. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note> common opinion is, that although <hi>in foro conſcientiae</hi> two of theſe preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions be ſufficient, to make a uſurer; yet <hi>in</hi>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">Bald. in l. emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione C. plus vae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere. &amp; in c. <hi>1.</hi> de feodo dato in vic. leg. com. Paul de Caſtro íne. ad noſtram. Et multi alij.</note> 
                     <hi>foro litigioſo</hi> three muſt concurre to condemne him. In the Leviticall law,<note n="g" place="margin">Levit. 25.27.</note> whenſoeuer the ſeller would redeeme his inheritance (<note n="h" place="margin">28.</note> vnleſſe it were a houſe in a Citie) he might, and account the fruits, from the ſale till the redeeming, in part of payment. But that was in reſpect of the Iubilie, when the ſeller was to haue his land againe<note n="i" place="margin">30.</note> freely: and the neerer that was, the leſſe worth was his land.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:6252:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>2</hi> All Vſury is unlawfull, and the taking of uſurie is ſinne; becauſe it is againſt the law of God, of Nature, of the Church, of the Common-wealth.</head>
               <p n="1">1 IT is againſt the law of God, and his will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed in his word:<note n="a" place="margin">Exo. 22.25.</note> 
                  <hi>When thou lendeſt money to my people the poore with thee, thou ſhalt not be to them like a</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">What maner of Creditor. ſee pag.</note> 
                  <hi>Creditor: ye ſhall not impoſe uſurie upon them.</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Levit. 25.35.36.</note> 
                  <hi>If thy brother with thee goe downe, and his hand doe ſhake, thou ſhalt ſtay him: and let him liue with thee a ſtranger and ſojourner. Thou ſhalt not take of him Vſurie and lone, but feare thy God and let thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther liue with thee.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">37.</note> 
                  <hi>Thy money thou ſhalt not giue to him upon uſurie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">38.</note> 
                  <hi>nor upon increaſe ſhalt thou giue thy foode: I am the Lord your God, which brought you out of the land of Egypt, to giue you the land of Canaan, to be to you God.</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Deut. 23.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not uſurie to thy brother, uſurie of money,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">20.</note> 
                  <hi>uſurie of food, uſurie of any thing, which is lent-to-uſurie. To an Aliant thou ſhalt lend-to-uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, but to thy brother thou ſhalt not lend-to-uſurie: that the Lord thy God may bleſſe thee, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 15.5.</note> 
                  <hi>His money he hath not given upon uſurie:</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Ezech. 18.13</note> 
                  <hi>upon uſurie hee giveth, and loue he taketh, ſhall he liue?</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">17.</note> 
                  <hi>Vſurie and lone he doeth not take, he ſhall not die.</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Pro. 28 8.</note> 
                  <hi>He that increaſeth his ſubſtance by uſurie and lone.</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Luke 6.35.</note> 
                  <hi>Lend, hoping for nothing of them.</hi> In which places of Scripture, I would have you to note firſt the nature of the uſurie for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden out of theſe phraſes: 1 That God forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>foenerare</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to uſurie,</hi> or to exerciſe <hi>uſurie,</hi> which verbe importeth generally all practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of uſurie, and taking gaine or conſideration for lending. 2 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>to giue upon uſurie,</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:6252:13"/>
which phraſe is uſed in contractes, if the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances doe beare it, as<note n="k" place="margin">Deut. 7.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not giue thy daughter to his ſonne:</hi> as here it may import a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract betweene the putter and the taker, the Uſurer and the Uſer: for free giving is excluded by <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhech.</hi> 3 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>to impoſe uſurie upon,</hi> which phraſe the holy Ghoſt uſeth in things ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted of men againſt their willes, and impoſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, as burthens are: as,<note n="l" place="margin">1. Reg. 12.4.</note> 
                  <hi>My father did put a burthen upon you.</hi> 4 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>to receiue uſurie,</hi> which phraſe is uſed alſo euen in thoſe thinges which are voluntarie: and under the ſame forme of words, as a bribe or reward is ſaid to be receiued, which is neither compacted nor exacted, but moſt freely offered, and yet prohibited and condemned, as in the ſame Chap. and verſe of <hi>Ezichiel:</hi>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Ezech. 18.17 22.12.</note> 
                  <hi>They receiue rewardes in thee, they receiue uſurie in thee.</hi> Of this<note n="n" place="margin">Hier. in Ezech. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>S. Ierome</hi> ſpeaketh: <hi>Some for lending their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney receiue preſents or giftes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly I would you note out of the ſame pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the hainouſneſſe of the offence, which appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, becauſe uſurie is contrary to the feare of God, <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.36. a forgetting of God, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 22.12. a ſinne againſt the firſt Commandement, I am the Lord thy God which brought thee out of the land of Egypt, <hi>Levit.</hi> 25.37. and therefore the uſurer depriued of Gods temporall bleſſing, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.10. made ſubiect to Gods temporall curſe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.8. and to the Magiſtrates puniſhment, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 5.7. hated of God, in ſo much that he claps his hands at him, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 22.13. ſhut out from Gods tabernacle,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6252:14"/>
and from the reſt upon his holy hill, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.1. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from eternall life, and made ſubject to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall death. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 18.</p>
               <p>Now for the cloaking of uſurie, it is ſo farre from leſſening the offence, that it doth augment it: as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſaid truely:<note n="o" place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſ. <hi>63.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Simulata aequitas, non eſt aequitas, ſed duplex iniquitas, quia &amp; iniquitas eſt, &amp; ſimulata. Diſſembled equitie is no equitie, but dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble iniquitie; becauſe it is both iniquitie and diſsimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> For God who is,<note n="p" place="margin">Luk. 16.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and knoweth the heart, can diſcerne their uſurie under their <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, their painted viſards, &amp; goodly cloakes: who loueth ſimplicitie and plaine dealing, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth all hypocriſie and diſſimulation: as<note n="q" place="margin">Pro. 11.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>The</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> qui ſimulant &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulant, &amp; ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie recti fallunt.</note> 
                  <hi>ſubtill in heart are abomination to the Lord, but the ſimple in way are his delight.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 It is againſt the law of Nature, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peere by theſe fiue conſiderations and arguments. Firſt the Uſurer receiueth two recompences or ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactions for one thing; one of them being ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivalent (contrarie to that<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ariſt. Pol. l. <hi>1.</hi> Plato de leg l. <hi>6</hi>
                  </note> aequalitie which is the rule of humane ſocietie) in that he requireth firſt reſtitution of his owne, that is, as much as hee deliuered: Secondly gaine for the uſe; whereas in mutuating (as before hath beene ſhewed) the thing and the uſe are but one, and cannot be ſeuered. For the<note n="t" place="margin">Aquin. <hi>2.2.</hi> q. <hi>78.</hi> art. <hi>1.</hi> ad. <hi>6.</hi> ff. Actomod. l. <hi>1. §</hi> penall. &amp; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nali. &amp; l. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> uſing of it is the ſpending of the verie thing.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the Uſurer maketh gaine of that, which is none of his owne, but another mans. For the propertie of the thing mutuated was transfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6252:14"/>
and alienated, and paſſed away from the len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the borrower: ſo that if the borrower paie any thing for the uſe of it, he paieth<note n="a" place="margin">Scot. in ſent. l. <hi>4.</hi> diſ. <hi>15.</hi> Lactant. devero cultu. l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>18.</hi>
                  </note> for his owne, and of his owne, which is plaine contrarie to<note n="b" place="margin">Suum cui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>.</note> Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice diſtributiue, which yeeldeth everie one his owne.</p>
               <p>Thirdly the Uſurer maketh<note n="c" place="margin">Scot. in ſent. <hi>4.</hi> dist. <hi>3.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Ariſtoph. in Nub.</note> priuate gaine of that which is common, that is of times; contrarie to the rule of humane ſocietie:<note n="d" place="margin">Cauſ. <hi>12.</hi> q. <hi>2.</hi> c. qui manumit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur.</note> 
                  <hi>Quod eſt commune omnium non erit particulare ſingulorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly the Uſurer maketh that<note n="e" place="margin">Ariſt. pol. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> breed, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and increaſe, which by nature is barren and unapt to increaſe:<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. ibidem.</note> for in uſurie money genders, gets, or bringes foorth money; whereupon <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarke</hi> ſaith, that the Uſurer maketh ſomething of nothing, mauger the head of the naturall Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher.</p>
               <p>Fiftly the Uſurer perverteth that end and uſe of money, which is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> agreeable to nature: namely commutation,<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Ariſt. ibidem.</note> for commutation was the end wherefore money was ordeined in humane ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie; and is the uſe of it, which naturall uſe the Uſurer turneth into that which is againſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nature, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Therefore it is called a kinde of<note n="h" place="margin">Sodomia na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae. Hug. Card. in Pſ. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> Sodomie. <hi>From theſe grounds and principles pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded thoſe many both wiſe lawes, and woorthy ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of thee Heathen, ledde onely by the ſtarre-light of reaſon, and deſtitute of the light of Gods word, against uſurie: which you may ſee at large in other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 It is againſt the lawes of the Church, which doth forbid uſurie to the<note n="i" place="margin">Con. Nic. c. <hi>18.</hi> Con. Arelat. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi> Con. Colon. p <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>31.</hi> Con. Laod. c. <hi>15</hi> Con. Carthag. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>17.</hi> Con. Tur. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1</hi>
                  </note> Clergie under penaltie
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6252:15"/>
of depriuation both of Communion and Benefice; and to the<note n="i" place="margin">Con. Eliber. c. <hi>20.</hi> Con. Lat. p. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>23.</hi> Con. Lugd. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>3</hi>
                  </note> Laitie under the penalties of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, of diſannulling their willes and teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, of excluding them from Chriſtian buriall, and many other. And the<note n="k" place="margin">Canones Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodi London anno. <hi>1584.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> law of our Church doth ſet and account uſurie in the ranke and num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of moſt hainous ſinnes, as haereſie, ſchiſme, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt, adulterie.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Laſtly it is againſt the temporall law of our owne common-wealth, both common and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute. The Common law doth puniſh uſurie, by<note n="l" place="margin">Glanvil. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note> confiſcation of all the Uſurers goods to the Kings uſe: and the ſtatute law now in force, though it pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſome kinde of uſurie (<hi>viz.</hi> ten in the hundreth or under) ſomewhat lightly in compariſon of that heinouſneſſe of the ſinne which the ſtatute doth acknowledge in that uſurie: yet it doth plainely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme,<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eliz.</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</note> 
                  <hi>that all uſurie is forbidden by the law of God, and is ſinne and deteſtable.</hi> Which determination of that high Court ought to be prohibition enough to everie true ſubject under the ſame go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, to avoid it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>3</hi> The objections and anſwers.</head>
               <p>INſteed of the objections againſt this trueth ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged heere, I will take in hand the booke, which is written of purpoſe in the defence of uſurie, as the author plainely<note n="n" place="margin">In his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to Prov. 28.8.</note> profeſſeth; by the confutation whereof, the arguments alſo urged in this confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence will receiue their ſatisfaction. In this booke firſt there are fiue queſtions propounded, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by M. <hi>C.</hi> whereof the firſt is.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:6252:15"/>
                  <hi>Whether the commandement of God giuen to forbid uſurie to the Iewes.</hi> Exod. 22. Levit. 25. Deut. 23.<note place="margin">M. C.</note> 
                  <hi>be generall and perpetuall, or not.</hi> The anſwere is. <hi>The commaundement of not biting, or oppreſsing with uſurie is generall and perpetuall; albeit it were permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Iewes becauſe of the heardneſſe of their harts, that they might oppreſſe the nations with uſurie, which before the comming of Chriſt were foreners from the kingdome of God: which yet is no more permitted vnto Chriſtians, than for every light cauſe to put away their Wives: And even this permiſsion for a time prooueth that the law, whereof the queſtion is moved is perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall. For the Iewes being ſo hard harted as divers vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull things were faine to be permitted them, there is no likelihood, that the Lood would have laid this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement vpon them,</hi> nempe, <hi>that they ſhould not take uſurie of their bretheren, unleſſe the law of God had neceſſarilie required the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, the ſubſtance of this anſwere I allow,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> that thoſe lawes are generall and perpetuall, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the commaundement of taking uſury of ſtrangers, which commaundement I doe not take to be a permiſſion of the nature of that, whereby a man did for a light cauſe put away his wife, as he maketh it. The difference I will not ſtand to ſhew, pertayning not to this queſtion. The truth of this anſwere is better confirmed by other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; as that <hi>David</hi> reckoneth it among morall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or rather among breaches of the morall law, as<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 15.5. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Baſil. ibid.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Slaunder, wrong-doing, perjurie, briberie, againſt the innocent;</hi> and<note n="b" place="margin">Ezech. 22.12</note> 
                  <hi>Ezechiel</hi> hedgeth it in betweene
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6252:16"/>
                  <hi>briberie, and deceite,</hi> and<note n="c" place="margin">Ezech. 18.12.13.</note> coupleth it with <hi>oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the poore, ſpoyling by violence, and Idolatrie,</hi> and therefore <hi>Ierome</hi> coupleth uſurie with deceit and robberie, <hi>Uſuras quaerere, aut fraudare, aut rapere ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil intereſt, quia ſeptimum praeceptum haec omnia pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibet.</hi> And S. <hi>Ambroſe: Siquis uſuram accipit, furtum facit.</hi> As for the precept for the Iewes to take uſurie of<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Deut. 23.20.</note> aliantes, that is,<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Eph. 2.12.</note> from the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of God, and the common-wealth of Iſraell; will make no more for the lawfulneſſe of uſurie, than the commaundement for the Iſraelites to<note n="f" place="margin">Exod. 11.2.</note> rob the Aegytians, or for <hi>Abraham</hi> to<note n="g" place="margin">Gen. 22.2.</note> kill his ſonne, will make for the lawfulneſſe of theft, or murder. Againſt the aliantes God commaunded<note n="h" place="margin">Am. lib. de Tobiac. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> worſe oppreſſion to be uſed than uſurie, and yet that is no reaſon to excuſe oppreſſion of other, or in other caſes, from being a breach of the morall law.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the interpretation which he maketh of theſe lawes by a diſtinction of <hi>biting, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsing,</hi> as though there were kinds of uſury, which were not <hi>biting, and oppreſsing,</hi> and therefore not forbidden; will appeare ſtraightway to be frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous. And ſo unnaturall and forced it is, that him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe forgetteth it in the end of his former wordes, when he doth expound thoſe commaundements generally <hi>of taking uſurie of their brethren;</hi> avouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>that the Law of God requireth neceſſarily that we ſhould not take uſurie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">M. C.</note>The ſecond queſtion. <hi>If thoſe lawes be generall and perpetuall, whether yet it may be lawfull in any rate,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6252:16"/>
or ſort to lend for gaine vnto ſuch men as are rich, and wealthie, upon covenantes, and bonds to receive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, or more then the principall; for that they are not poore, nor fallen in decay, neither doe borrow for neede, but to purchaſe, or to compaſſe great matters to increaſe their riches, and wealth thereby?</hi> Anſwere. <hi>It is lawfull notwithſtanding the law to lend to uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, conſidering that the end of the law is love: See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore it is not againſt the love of thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſo to lend as both the lender, and the borrower may in all good likelihood be profited; there can be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing herein againſt love, if the affection be not worſe then the action of lending, and borrowing in this kind. Yet ſuch may be the lender, himſelfe not being able to occupie his money in any lawfull trade; and ſuch the borrower able well to traffique with the ſame, that not onely the perſons lending, and borrowing with their families, but the common-wealth alſo ſhall be profited thereby, and hurt otherwiſe, if that the money of the lender be not imployed, or the cunning and skill of the borrower lye idle, and dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this ſecond queſtion,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> and anſwere note firſt that he putteth his caſe of plaine uſurie, that is, <hi>to lend for gaine, and to receive increaſe, and more than the principall;</hi> and that compacted uſurie too: <hi>upon covenant,</hi> and moreover ſtrongly ſecured, <hi>upon bondes.</hi> Secondly, note his limitation of this uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, both in reſpect of the perſon of the borrower, <hi>ſuch men as are rich, and wealthie, not poore, and fallen in decay,</hi> and alſo in reſpect of the end, <hi>to purchaſe, or to compaſſe great matters withall, to increaſe their
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6252:17"/>
riches, and wealth thereby, not for neede.</hi> This <hi>neede</hi> is expreſſed in his anſwere to the third, and fourth queſtions which concerne borrowing upon uſury <hi>(which I omit to ſet downe here, becauſe they belong not to the queſtion of lending upon uſurie, neither will I ſtand with him therein) to be for his neceſſarie uſe of preſervation of himſelfe, and his familie,</hi> and <hi>for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of his eſtate, and inheritance,</hi> under which are contayned as well occupiers, which live by their trades; as owners, which live by their rents; and farmers, which live by husbanding other mens landes: <hi>Ergo,</hi> by this limitation and reſtriction, and by confeſſion of M. <hi>C.</hi> all lending upon uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the poore, that never attayned competent wealth, though it be to purchaſe and compaſſe ſome matter to bring them out of povertie: or to the decayed, till they be out of decay, and have recovered their former eſtates; or to noblemen, gentlemen, and other rich men, which are in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying, and in daunger to impaire, and diminiſh their eſtate and inheritance, or have not preſently to preſerve themſelves, and their families anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rablie to their eſtate, without borrowing for a time, is forbidden by thoſe lawes. And this is enough to breake the necke of uſurie, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne all the Uſurers in England, I thinke.</p>
               <p>M. <hi>C.</hi> in his anſwere to the fourth queſtion maketh <hi>a quaere: whether he that is driven to borrow upon uſurie to preſerve his eſtate, and inheritance, were not better to borrow of a man of no ſound religion, than of one that profeſſeth the truth, although in all other
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6252:17"/>
traffique the law of God doth drawe us rather to deale with thoſe which are of the houſehold of faith, than with ſtrangers.</hi> Which argueth, that he holdeth the lending to ſuch a one to be ſinne, at the leaſt in the lender. So then M. <hi>C.</hi> reſolution is, that it is lawfull to take uſurie onely of the rich, and wealthie, and that of them too onely then, when they borrow to purchaſe, or to compaſſe ſome great matter, to increaſe their riches, and wealth. Now this thing which is lawfull in the lender, is unlawfull in the borrower, as M. <hi>C.</hi> avouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in his anſwere to the fourth queſtion in theſe wordes. <hi>Every man may not borrow lawfully, much leſſe of uſurie: For albeit it be no ſinne to borrow, yet it is a puniſhment for ſinne: and a correction which God layeth upon his children when they be driven to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, &amp;c. Wherefore it being a curſe of the Law, and a matter wherein every one of the children of God ſhould be humbled, it is alſo cleare that a man ought not for light cauſes to throwe downe himſelfe into this curſe, as for example, to increaſe his eſtate, being able other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to mainetaine himſelfe honeſtly, &amp;c.</hi> Whereby it appeareth, that the lender to uſurie in this caſe, muſt needes be helping, and acceſſarie to the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowers offence, and a cauſe of an unlawfull thing, which himſelfe might prevent, and remedie. Now let every Chriſtian man judge, whether to lend to uſurie, even in this caſe here propounded, be not a fearefull thing in this regard, that an other man is thereby brought under the curſe of Gods law.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, let us waigh his reaſons for the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6252:18"/>
of this one kinde of uſurie. The firſt is: <hi>It is not againſt loue:</hi> Ergo, <hi>not againſt the law: for love is the ende of the law.</hi> This very reaſon is uſed by the wicked <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> that wrote the defence of Adulterie. <hi>Whatſoever is of love, is neither againſt the law, nor diſliked of God: but to lye with another mans wife begins of love, proceedes by love, and ends with love: Ergo, &amp;c.</hi> And he addeth the correction, or limitation which this Author here doth, <hi>ſo that the affection be not worſe than the action.</hi> For ſome kinde of Adultery he condemneth, as this doth ſome kinde of uſurie. If M. <hi>C.</hi> would anſwere this argument for Adulterie, he ſhould eaſilie per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the weakneſſe of it for uſurie. To lend indeed is an office of love, a worke of Chriſtianitie,<note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 15. Luk. 6.</note> a commaundement of God: and to take uſurie for the lending is of love too: but it is <hi>the love of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>Paul</hi> calleth it, and maketh it<note n="a" place="margin">1. Tim. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>the roote of all evill;</hi> as for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourly love, or brotherly love it is quite contrary unto it; as one ſaid:<note n="b" place="margin">Hug. Card. in Pſ. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Uſura directe opponitur chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati: Uſurie is directly contrary to charitie:</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore forbidden by it, as another ſaid:<note n="c" place="margin">Bez. annot. in Math. <hi>19.8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Foenerari pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibet Chriſtiana charitas. Chriſtian love forbiddeth to put to uſurie. Baſil</hi> ſaid truely, <hi>Men gather not grapes of thiſtles, nor figges of thornes,</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Baſil. hom. in uſus.</note> 
                  <hi>nor love of uſurie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond reaſon is as it were an Epilogiſme to the former. <hi>So to lend as the lender and the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower may in al good likelihood be profited, is not againſt love; But in the uſurie above ſpecified, and qualified both the lender, and the borrower may in all good like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6252:18"/>
be profited. Ergo, that kinde of uſurie is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt love.</hi> I deny the <hi>minor,</hi> with a double diſtinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: firſt of the perſons, for in reſpect of the len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it is paſt likelihood, becauſe his profit (for ſo they terme uſurie) is certaine, and ſufficiently ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and made moſt ſure: and likewiſe in reſpect of the borrower it is paſt likelihood, for his loſſe is<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Baſil. ibid.</note> certain, becauſe whatſoever he giveth for the uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is loſſe to him, his ſubſtance being ſo much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed: and therefore <hi>Baſil</hi> calleth all uſurie<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Baſil. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>gaine of loſſe.</hi> For it goeth out of his owne to the decreaſe thereof. Which may further appeare by the other diſtinction: in this action there are two things: firſt, <hi>Mutuating,</hi> by which together with the uſers induſtrie, and Gods bleſſing groweth the gaine, if any be: ſecondly, uſurie or gaine to be paid for that lending, and that is ſo far from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiting the payer of it, that it impayreth his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſo much as it is. This diſtinction<note n="g" place="margin">Heming. in fac. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Hemin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius</hi> hath; <hi>No good can come by uſurie of it ſelfe, but if there ſeeme by chaunce any good to come of uſurie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Non uſuris ſed mutuation.</note> 
                  <hi>that is not to be attributed to the uſurie, but to the lending.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now this profit which he ſuppoſeth to come to the borrower by the uſurie, is but <hi>in all good likelihood,</hi> as he confeſſeth; there is no certaintie in it; and yet he will have the uſurie, and increaſe to the lender not onely certaine, but aſſured by bond: is not this great inequalitie, and injuſtice? What if the borrower be indeede at loſſe by the uſing of that money? ſo that he cannot make up
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6252:19"/>
his Principall againe to repay the lender, will the lender beare part of that loſſe? No I warrant you. But ſay the borrower doth gaine, and get wealth, notwithſtanding he pay uſurie, as perhaps ſome may; though in compariſon of them that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done by it, they be very few, as <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaid, <hi>Many, ſayest thou, are made rich by uſurie:</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Baſil. hom. ad v. uſur.</note> 
                  <hi>more, thinke I, have come to the halter by it:</hi> Yet that they gaine is not to be attributed to the uſurie, but to the good bargaines they met withall, their skill in traffique, and principally to God bleſſing their induſtry, and labour: whereby they have reaſonable gaine to live by, and to increaſe by, beſide that which the Uſurer taketh; and ſhall this excuſe the Uſurers of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, which taketh away that which is none of his owne, but another mans, though he take not all the other mans, but leave him part for himſelfe? If a theife meeting me, as I come from the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, take from me but part of that I have gayned there, leaving me enough to countervaile my charges and ſomewhat over, ſhall his theft be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed? I will conclude this point with <hi>Leos</hi> words not much varying the ſence.<note n="a" place="margin">Leo ſerm. <hi>6.</hi> de jejun deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi menſis. c. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Quilibet ſequatur eventus, mala eſt ratio foenerantis. What event ſoever follow the Uſurers caſe is naught.</hi> This argument he preſſeth by conſideration of the eſtate as well of the lender as of the borrower; <hi>the lender</hi> wanting skill to imploy his money; <hi>the borrower</hi> having skill, but wanting wherewithall to uſe it; ſo that <hi>diviſim</hi> both the ones money, and the others skill lyeth idle to the dammage of themſelves, and of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6252:19"/>
the common-wealth, but <hi>conjunctim</hi> they may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite themſelves, and the common-wealth too. All this is true: but what concludeth he hereof? mary, <hi>ergo,</hi> it is lawfull to put to uſurie to the rich, <hi>to purchaſe withall, or to compaſſe great matters to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe their wealth.</hi> Marke how the premiſes croſſe the concluſion: the premiſes deſcribe a borrower, whoſe cunning and skill lyeth idle and dead, which muſt be by need, or want of wherewithall, which is povertie: for were he rich himſelfe, his skill nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not to lye idle, much leſſe to be dead. The concluſion deſcribeth a man that is rich, and wealthy. So then here is the coherence of this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument: by lending to the skilfull poore which want wherewithall to imploy their skill, the poore may be maintained, and the common-wealth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefited. <hi>Ergo,</hi> It is lawfull to lend to the rich and wealthy to purchaſe, or to compaſſe great matters to increaſe their wealth. So then we are cleane gone from the queſtion which was propoſed of the rich, and wealthie, and are come to the poore, and needy. Now let us conſider how this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment holdeth for them. The money of the lender wanting skill, and the skill of the needy borrower wanting wherewithall to uſe it, will both lye idle: <hi>Ergo,</hi> that lender may put his money to uſurie to this borrower. How this conſequence doth hold, you may coniecture by theſe: A man having a wife being himſelfe unfruitfull, wanteth children to the decay of his houſe, and dammage of the common-wealth. <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is lawfull for another that
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6252:20"/>
is fruitfull, to lye with his wife, to ſupply theſe wants, or thus: A rich man hath a barne full of corne, but cannot threſh it out, to the hinderance of the common-wealth, and himſelfe; another be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able and skilfull to threſh, hath no corne to threſh: <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is lawfull for this fellow to breake up the others barne, threſh his corne, ſteale part for himſelfe, and leave the reſt ready for the others uſe; here both may be benefited, and the common-wealth too: oh ſay you; but there are other lawful meanes to remedie both theſe inconveniences; the rich man may hire another to threſh his corne; and pay him his wages, holding his owne; the poore may threſh for hire, and receive wages for his maintenance. Even ſo it is in our caſe propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, there are remedies ſufficient provided in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſocietie, without uſurie, that neither the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of him that is not able to uſe it, may lye idle; nor the skill of him, that hath not wherewithall to uſe it, may lye dead: among other there is ſociety, whereby both theſe two may joine together, and relying upon Gods providence, the one venturing his money, the other his skill, by Gods bleſſing may benefite themſelves, &amp; their families, and the common-wealth too. But the Uſurer likes not this; he loves not to truſt to Gods providence: he can provide well enough for himſelfe; as <hi>Ajax</hi> anſwered his father.<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Sophoc. in Ajace.</note> 
                  <hi>I will vanquiſh, &amp; have victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and that without God.</hi> Touching the profit which commeth by uſurie, it is true, that unto the Uſurer nothing can be of greater yeeld, no gaine
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6252:20"/>
comparable to it: but to the needy occupier (as <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaith) uſurie doth not bring<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Baſil. ibid.</note> a full remiſſion, but a little intermiſſion of want, and hard fortune. <hi>No man can heale a wound with a wound, nor cure a ſore with a ſore,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>neither can any man remedie neede by uſurie: for how is it poſsible that money ſhould</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flow and multiply ſo exceſsively as to ſalve thy need, and ſatisfie the Principall, and</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>beget the uſurie too</hi> ſaith <hi>Baſil;</hi> and <hi>Plutark compareth it, even as if a man that is not able to cary a Kid, ſhould crave to have a great Oxe laid upon his ſhoulders.</hi> And for the profit which may redound to the common-wealth by uſurie, I will tell you what it is; the occupier to make gaines of the wares bought with uſury mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney as will ſerve to ſuſtaine himſelfe, to repay the Principall, and withall to ſatisfie the uſurie, muſt hold up his wares the dearer, uſe the more craft and deceite, lying, and ſwearing, to ſell them the better, to the oppreſſion of the common-wealth. So that <hi>Chryſostome</hi> ſaid truely that the <hi>Uſurer was the common enimie of all:</hi> and <hi>Baſil</hi> ſetteth downe the commodities of uſurie,<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>lying, ingratitude, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaving, forſwearing,</hi> and <hi>Plutark reckoneth up lying, and forgeing, as fruites of uſurie.</hi> As for any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie which may accrew to the common-wealth by purchaſing with uſurie money, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not imagine, unleſſe the Purchaſers rent-rearing and racking of Farmers to make up his money for die uſurer, be a commoditie to the common-wealth.</p>
               <p>Unto this anſwere of M. <hi>C.</hi> there is annexed a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6252:21"/>
defence thereof by another, who would faine goe a little further, and have uſurie, that is ſo qualified as in the anſwere to the former queſtion is ſet downe, to be a thing commaunded, yet he will not at the firſt daſh avouch it plainly, but inſinuatingly commeth in with his <hi>if.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Defendor.</note>
                  <hi>If it be not a thing which in ſome caſe may truely be ſaid, to he commaunded, yet at the leaſt it is in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe actions which are indifferent, and free, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be uſed, or not uſed, according to the inducement of perſons, time, and place counſelling or diſcounſelling the ſame.</hi> His reaſons, and arguments I will ſet downe in his owne wordes, and anſweare them briefly.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Defendor.</note>
                  <hi>To this purpoſe of the indifferencie, and freedome of the action to uſe it, or not to uſe it, commeth firſt the word it ſelfe of</hi> uſurie, <hi>which in the learned tounges ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth a middle, and indifferent nature apt aſwell to note a lawfull limitation of the thing whereto it is applied, as to ſignifie that which is unlawfull.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note>Firſt, this aſſumption of his is falſe: for the names of uſurie in the learned tounges are not apt to ſignifie an indifferent thing. <hi>Neſheck</hi> in Hebrue hath no aptneſſe to ſignifie a lawfull action, which is the name of uſurie in generall: neither <hi>Nuchte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha,</hi> nor <hi>Chibbuliah</hi> in the Chaldaean toung: nor <hi>faenus</hi> in the Latin tongue: nor <hi>Tarbith</hi> in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue tongue: for <hi>Tarbith</hi> is ever uſed for a thing unlawfull, and condemned: and ſo is the Engliſh <hi>Uſurie,</hi> as himſelfe confeſſeth, though he lay the fault upon the ignorance of the vulger people:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6252:21"/>
whereas it is in the nature and propertie of the thing which it is applyed to ſignifie. Secondly, this conſequence <hi>the name is apt to note a thing indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent.</hi> Ergo, <hi>the thing which in common ſpeech it is applied to ſignifie is indifferent</hi> is altogether inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient. This aptneſſe to note muſt be either in the Etymologie, or in the uſe, and by this argument I could defend great ſinnes. Adulterie in the learned Latin tongue hath his name of <hi>ad</hi> and <hi>alter:</hi> Now what is apter to ſignifie a thing indifferent than <hi>alter, another?</hi> and for the uſe, when a doore is opened not with his owne key, but of another doore it is called <hi>clavis adulterinus:</hi> when a letter is ſigned not with the ſeale of the writer, but of another, it is called <hi>ſignum adulterina:</hi> and either of theſe may be lawfully, or unlawfully done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the inducement of the circumſtances of perſons, place, or time, counſelling, or diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelling the ſame: and what? ſhall I with this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendor conclude: <hi>Ergo,</hi> adulterie in ſome caſe may be lawful or indifferent? Likewiſe fornication com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of <hi>fornix, an arch, or a roome built archwiſe.</hi> Which is a lawfull thing, and hath an aptneſſe to ſignifie an indifferent thing, a place apt as well for lawful copulation, as unlawful: is therfore fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in ſome caſe indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? A thiefe in the learned Latin tongue is called <hi>fur, a ferendo of bringing</hi> as<note n="a" place="margin">Sipont.</note> ſome ſay; or of <hi>furus</hi> that is <hi>furvus, blacke, or darke,</hi> as<note n="b" place="margin">Noun. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel. de prop. ſerm. Varro de ling. Lat. l. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> other more ancient ſay: and in Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>to hide, or keepe cloſe:</hi> all which are of a middle, and indifferent nature, apt as well to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6252:22"/>
a thing lawfull, as unlawfull. Yea by this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>tyrannie</hi> may be better maintained than <hi>uſury;</hi> for the worde in the learned tongues both Greeke and Latine is of a middle, and indifferent nature, apt by his etymologie, and applied by uſe to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie either a good or a bad King. By this you may ſee alſo the vaineneſſe of this argument drawne from the Greeke worde <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which properly ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth that which a living creature procreateth or bringeth foorth by generation, and becauſe (as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith) as the living creature in generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on bringeth foorth more of the ſame kinde, or his like: ſo money put to uſurie bringeth foorth his like, that is, more money, therefore uſurie is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is a thing generated of the ſame kinde. Now commeth this Defendor and argueth thus: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifieth children which are gotten by generation; and children are ſome legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate, and ſome illegitimate; and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifieth alſo uſurie, <hi>ergo,</hi> uſurie is ſome lawfull, and ſome unlawfull. It is a plaine <hi>Paralogiſme ab aequivoco: Lupus</hi> ſignifieth a Woolfe, and woolves haue tailes: and <hi>Lupus</hi> ſignifieth alſo a ſnaffle, <hi>ergo,</hi> ſome ſnaffles have tailes. Even as good as this: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifieth to hide, and that may be done ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lawfully, or unlawfully: and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifieth alſo to ſteale: <hi>ergo</hi> ſtealing may be done either lawfully, or unlawfully. And why not this: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifieth that which is begotten, and procreated by generation, as children, and the children are begotten of male, and female, and are themſelues
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6252:22"/>
ſome male, ſome female: and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifieth alſo the uſurie money which is begot of the principall: <hi>ergo</hi> uſurie money is begot of a male, and a female: and ſome uſurie money is male, and ſome female. This is ſomewhat likelier than the other: for there are ſome <hi>Edward</hi> peeces, &amp; ſome <hi>Elizabeth</hi> peeces; and <hi>Phillips, and Maries</hi> may ſtand for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>In handling of this argument he goeth about to meet with an objection out of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> making us beleeve that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> maketh for him.<note place="margin">Arist. Pol. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ariſtotle Pol. l.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. condemning uſurie altogether, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other reaſons uſeth this: Whoſoever lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the uſe of a thing which is agreeable to the end, and nature of it, and maketh a uſe contrarie to the end, and nature of it, is to be condemned: but the uſurer leaveth that uſe of money which is agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the end, and nature of it, and maketh a uſe contrarie to the end, and nature of it; <hi>ergo, &amp;c.</hi> The <hi>minor</hi> he prooveth, becauſe money was ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for commutation, and the nature of it is to ſerve thereto in humane ſocietie, which uſe the uſurer leaveth altogether: againe to make money breed, ingender, or bring foorth money is againſt nature: for money hath no ſuch gendring, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creating nature, being naturally barren: but the uſurer maketh his money gender, and procreate more money, that is, more in the ſame kinde. Wherefore <hi>Baſil</hi> termeth uſurie <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a beaſt of a ſtrange and monſtrous nature,</hi> in bringing foorth, differing from other creatures:<note place="margin">Baſil. hom ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. uſur.</note> which he ſheweth, becauſe other creatures <hi>have a time to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6252:23"/>
bring foorth perfect yongue: but the uſurers money is borne to day, and to day begins to bring foorth. Other creatures the ſooner they ingender, the ſooner they leave of ingendring: but the uſurers money ingendreth quickly, and never leaveth off: Other creatures com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to their growth are at a ſtande: but the uſurers money is ever growing. Other creatures delivering over their breeding to their yongue, leave off teeming themſelves, but the uſurers money, both that is newly borne, doth beget, and the old principall is youthful ſtil.</hi> To the ſecond part of <hi>Ariſtotles minor</hi> this defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor anſwereth, that <hi>Ariſtotle condemneth onely that uſurie which is practized with the neighbours loſſe, and onely for this cauſe that the Uſurer taketh it whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the debtor hath gained, or not.</hi> Whereas in <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> there is no ſuch thing, nor the leaſt inkling of any ſuch diſtinction. <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> ſpeech is general, his arguments cary with them a generalitie, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there in him one title tending that way. Yes, ſaith he,<note place="margin">Defendor.</note> 
                  <hi>The very words doe ſhew it, where he ſaith, money is barren, and doth not beget money, that is, if it be alone, and of it ſelfe: and who denyeth this; money in a cheſt, or hid in the ground doth not beget money: but that wares may be bought with it, and ſo by mans induſtrie gaine be made, who can deny? Therefore we ſay, gaine may be taken of the gaine, not money of the bare money.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> Who ever heard ſuch an abſurd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite; that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſpeaking of the unnaturalneſſe of money begetting money in uſurie, meaneth of money taken upon uſurie to be locked in a cheſt, or to digge it in the ground? No not old <hi>Euclio in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6252:23"/>
Plautus,</hi> I warrant you, would pay uſurie for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, to pot up, and put in the ground, as well as he loved it. If any were ever ſo witleſſe, ſhall we thinke that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> intreating of the common ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie of mankind, the weale publike, and the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique ſtate, ever dreamed of ſuch doing? No, he ſpake of that uſurie which was in uſe, and common practize: But ſee the abſurd conſequence of the reſt. <hi>Wares may be bought with money:</hi> true, for that is the right ende of money; commutation: <hi>A man by his induſtrie may make gaine of his wares,</hi> true, or elſe all trade and traffique were in vaine: but what of all this? Mary, ſaith the Defendor, <hi>Ergo, the Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers bare money doth not yeeld him money.</hi> And why forſooth? what elſe commeth from the uſurer but the bare money? or for what is the uſurie money paid him, but for the bare money? the wares are none of his; the money which was paide for the wares was then none of his; the commutation was not made by him; the induſtrie is none of his; the venture is nothing to him; neither is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing his but the bare money which getteth him his uſurie money. If the Vſurer will plead ſocietie and ſo come in for a ſhare of the gaine, let him keepe the lawes of ſocietie according to the rule of equitie, and take his ſhare of the gaine, if any be in Gods name.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The next point, and the ſame the greateſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Defendor.</note> 
                  <hi>and most important</hi> (ſaith the Defendor) <hi>is to take a view of all thoſe places of Scripture which are commonly allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, as carriyng in them the ſentence of condemnation,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6252:24"/>
written in them, againſt all compact for increaſe of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney over and above the Principall, whereof the firſt is,</hi> Exo. 22.25. To avoid the conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation of this place he hath foure evaſions, all like to <hi>Adams</hi> fig-leaves.</p>
               <p>The firſt is this: <hi>In the</hi> 21.22.23.24. <hi>verſes he doth generally forbid the oppreſsion of the poore,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Defendor.</note> 
                  <hi>and deſtitute perſons; after verſe</hi> 25.26.27. <hi>that which before he had ſpoken of oppreſsion, he expreſſeth by the particularities, and the kindes thereof: now in the prohibition there being nothing ſpoken againſt, but that whereby any neighbour is oppreſſed, it cannot be that any thing is reckoned up in the particulars, but that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my neighbour is oppreſſed. There being then a kind of uſurie, and increaſe of money by contract which doth not oppreſſe my neighbour, but releiveth him, it must neceſſarily follow that uſurie is not here forbidden.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Uſurie is not a <hi>ſpecies,</hi> or a particular of the ſinne forbidden in the former verſes 21.22.23.24.<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> In thoſe verſes there are two ſeveral precepts, the one concerneth ſtrangers or ſojourners, the other toucheth widowes, and orphanes of the people. Theſe are <hi>diſparata:</hi> and therefore cannot have one <hi>ſpecies</hi> under them. Againe the perſons mentioned verſe 25. are <hi>Gods people</hi> the Iſraelites, and adde the adjunct unto them, <hi>the poore:</hi> it is the poore Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites: Now they cannot come under the <hi>Genus</hi> ſtrangers, for they are oppoſite: <hi>ſtranger, and Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelite:</hi> neither can they come under <hi>widdowes, and orphanes,</hi> but are divers kinds fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them: <hi>for widowes &amp; orphanes</hi> are reſpected, not in regard of poverty, unleſſe withall they be poore; but of their inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6252:24"/>
to menage worldly affaires, &amp; to withſtand wrong, and of their aptneſſe to be wronged: and if they be poore withall, then are they but a <hi>ſpecies</hi> of poore people. So that in reſpect of the perſons he ſhould rather have ſaid contrarily, that this 25. verſe had beene <hi>genus</hi> to the other before. Now for the ſinne forbidden againſt the ſtranger there are two things prohibited; firſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> R. D. Chimch. in lib. radicum.</note> which the Rabbines to diſtinguiſh from the other, doe inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret it, of an abuſe by words, as <hi>obraiding, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling:</hi> Now hereof uſurie cannot be a <hi>ſpecies:</hi> for uſurie is no verball matter; wordes will not ſerve the turne: If this interpretation be not liked, there will be little difference between this, and the other word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and that ſignifieth to preſſe, or thruſt with violence; as the <hi>Aſſe</hi> thruſt <hi>Balaams</hi> foote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the wall <hi>Num.</hi> 22. and as <hi>Elizeus</hi> comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Iehorams</hi> meſſenger to be uſed 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 6.32. <hi>cruſh him in the very doore,</hi> and <hi>metaphorically</hi> it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth that violent injurie, oppreſſion, and tyranny wherewith cruell kings cruſh, keepe under, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict their ſubjectes, as the caſe of the Iſraëlites was under the Kings of Aegypt, which <hi>Moſes</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth by this word.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>I have ſeene the affliction where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Aegyptians afflict them.</hi> Now that was plain tyranny in the Aegyptians, and ſlavery in the Iſraë<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites being forced to all kind of drudgerie by bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and bodily puniſhment, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſheweth. <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.13.14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.14. Now of this affliction uſurie can be no <hi>ſpecies,</hi> becauſe in uſurie there is no force or violence, but all amitie, and faire ſpeech
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6252:25"/>
as <hi>Baſil</hi> ſheweth, <hi>The Uſurer laugheth upon him, and remembreth the acquaintance be had with his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Baſil. hom. in uſur.</note> 
                  <hi>and calleth him good neighbour, and friend.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the widowes, and orphanes there is forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which hath the like ſignification, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> hath, that is, an unjuſt kind of handling with voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, as tyrannie, and ſervitude is: for <hi>Moſes</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth the tyrannie of the Aegyptians, and ſlave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the Iſraelites, with this word alſo. <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.11.12. <hi>&amp; Gen.</hi> 15.13. And <hi>Saraes</hi> violent uſage of <hi>Hagar</hi> is expreſſed with this word. <hi>Gen.</hi> 16. Now this cannot be a <hi>genus</hi> to uſurie, becauſe there is no violence, or force in uſurie, as before was ſaid. Theſe ſinnes are abuſes <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>of the iraſcible part of the ſoule:</hi> Uſurie is an abuſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>of the concupiſcible part:</hi> they are breaches of the ſixt commandement, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill.</hi> Uſurie a breach of the eight, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale:</hi> they are vices in exceſſe of the vertue, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Uſurie is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of the vertue <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as the Philoſopher ſpeaketh: and yet this learned man will haue one a <hi>ſpecies</hi> of the other.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Defendor.</note>The ſecond evaſion is this, <hi>The particular oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which is ſpoken of in the</hi> 26. <hi>and</hi> 27. <hi>verſes, being a thing not ſimply vnlawfull, but that which may be done in ſome caſe, it followeth that the former, which the holy Ghoſt hath made Par, and brother to it, is alſo not ſimply vnlawfull. As therefore there may bee a man of ſuch wealth and ſtore of garments, that a man may lawfully keepe his garment that hee hath pledged with him, not a night alone, but an whole yeere of nights:
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6252:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſo he may be ſuch an one to whom he hath let money, that he may lawfully expect any increaſe of money for the lone thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> The Antecedent is untrue: for the particular oppreſſion ſpoken of verſe 26.27. is ſimply unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and may not bee done in any caſe, that is for any creditor to take of any poore man for pawne, his garment, hauing none other to cover his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe withall, whether it be by day, or by night, as the Rabbines underſtand it of both. It is inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie to ſee a man goe naked, or lie naked with nothing upon him: and Chriſtianitie comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to couer ſuch: but it is immanitie and ſavage crueltie to make him goe naked, and to take from him that <hi>onely</hi> thing he hath to cover his nakednes: and that the law ſpeaketh onely of ſuch a pledge, is more then manifeſt, verſ. 27. <hi>For it is his onely cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, it is the very covering of his skin, wherein ſhall he lie?</hi> and of ſuch <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeaketh: <hi>They make</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Job. 24.7.9.</note> 
                  <hi>a man lie naked all night without a covering, and they take to pawne that which the poore hath on, and make him goe naked without a covering.</hi> And yet our Defendor commeth in with his rich man, that may ſpare one garment a yeere of nights, as though he dreamed of nothing but rich men, and wealth. Well, let us leaue him in this ſweete dreame of his, and come to his third evaſion, which is this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Both in the verſes before,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Defendor.</note> 
                  <hi>and in the preſent verſe in hand, he ſpeaketh of the poore, and deſtitute, yea and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry poore perſons, and therefore without injurie of the text, it cannot be ſtretched to all ſorts of men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:6252:26"/>
                  <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note>It is well that hee coupleth this verſe with the former verſes: for by them he may ſee the nature of this. In the verſes before, where he forbiddeth abuſing with termes, oppreſſing with violence, and afflicting, he ſpeaketh of the poore, yea of deſtitute in reſpect of abilitie defenſiue, namely of ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, widowes, or orphanes: therefore without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurie to the text, thoſe lawes cannot be ſtretched to all ſorts of men, but that we may lawfully abuſe in termes, oppreſſe, afflict any other being neither ſtranger, widow, nor orphane. If the Defendor will grant me this conſequence, I will ſtraine my ſelfe to grant him the other, and ſeeke ſome other anſwere to this evaſion. <hi>Sed quae est iſta dialectica: What Logique is this?</hi> ſaid M. <hi>Iewel. Solomon</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, <hi>rob not the poore, becauſe he is poore. Ergo,</hi> it is lawfull to rob the rich, becauſe he is rich. I adde the like out of <hi>Moſes: Moſes</hi> forbiddeth<note n="b" place="margin">Devt. 24.14. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>to defraud, or deceiue the hireling, that is poore and needie: Ergo,</hi> if he be rich and wealthie, I may defraud, and deceiue him. But in this kinde of Logique, I can helpe the Uſurers one ace beyond their Defendor: for as there is a limitation of the people to the poore, ſo that of the reſt of the people we may take uſury: ſo there is in this law a limitation alſo of the poore to one ſpeciall kind of poore, namely <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>the poore with thee.</hi> Now this addition <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>with thee,</hi> doth import not onely a vicinitie, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration, or dwelling together; for the holy ghoſt expreſſeth that with other phraſes, as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and ſuch like; but it importeth withall a bond be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6252:26"/>
them of Dominion, and ſervitude or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, as to be one of his familie, and within his ſervice, as we uſe alſo to ſpeake, <hi>he hath beene with me ſeaven yeeres,</hi> that is, hath ſerved me, or beene in my familie. Which alſo may appeare, becauſe the law ſpeaking of taking a brother into ſervice uſeth this word,<note n="a" place="margin">Levit. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>he ſhall be</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>with thee:</hi> and ſpeaking of the manumiſſion of ſuch an one uſeth the ſame word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">ibidem. Deut. 15.12.</note> 
                  <hi>from with thee,</hi> which is not a little inforced in the latter member of this law, which mentioneth <hi>impoſing upon;</hi> inſinuating a ſuperioritie over him. So then the law ſpeaking only of ſuch poor as are with me, under me, within my ſervice or familie, it cannot be without injurie to the text, to ſtretch it to all ſorts of poor, but that I may take uſury of ſuch poor as are not with me, are nothing to me, owe me no ſervice, &amp; perhaps dwel not neere me. Now I hope I have pleaſed the Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers with inlarging their libertie by following this Defendors Logique. But to returne to the place; there are many reaſons why in theſe lawes, and the like there is ſpeciall mention of theſe impotent perſons. Firſt, <hi>Lyra</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Lyr in Exod. <hi>22</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Lex exprimit illud quod frequentius accidit, ſcilicet afflictio talium, quia reſiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re nequeunt. The law expreſſeth that which uſually hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth, namely the afflicting of ſuch, becauſe they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not withſtand, or defend themſelves:</hi> Secondly, God uſeth in his lawes to expreſſe the groſeſt ſinnes, as <hi>murther, adulterie, theft,</hi> not allowing whatſoever commeth not to that degree, but in theſe condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that. Thirdly, God hereby would teſtifie to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6252:27"/>
the world his care over theſe deſtitute perſons, which of all other are leaſt cared for; and therefore he taketh them into his<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 68.6.146.9.</note> ſpeciall protection. Now if God forbidding to lend upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> uſurie to the poore, ſhould allow men to lend to uſurie to the rich, he ſhould have more care of the rich, than of the poore: for no man would lend to the poore freely, when he might lend to the rich for uſurie. Laſtly, I might deny, that this addition, <hi>the poore with thee,</hi> doth belong to that member which forbiddeth uſurie: for in lending money God forbids two thinges in that verſe: Firſt,<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>to be as a Creditor;</hi> ſuch an one as ſhall be deſcribed<note n="c" place="margin">Pag. 46.</note> 
                  <hi>anone:</hi> and here it was requiſite that the ſpecification of poore ſhould reſtraine it, becauſe otherwiſe it is not unlawfull, as appeareth, <hi>Deut.</hi> 24.10. Where there is a law made for the right and lawfull practize of it. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it is forbidden <hi>to impoſe uſurie:</hi> and this member hath no mention of poore, becauſe it is a generall prohibition, and ſomewhat it appeareth, that this prohibition differeth from the other, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the holy Ghoſt ſetteth it downe in a different forme of ſpeech, ſpeaking in this member plurally, whereas in the former he ſpake <hi>ſingularly.</hi> Howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be in this law, that the prohibition concern the poore onely, or all in generall; it is manifeſt, that in other lawes uſurie is generally forbidden, as <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.19. <hi>Thou ſhalt not put to uſurie to thy brother:</hi> here is no difference of poore, and rich, but a generall comprehenſion of all Iſraelites, and members of the Church, which may further ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6252:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
by the generall oppoſition <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antes. And ſo <hi>Pſ.</hi> 15.5. <hi>He that giveth not his money to uſurie:</hi> heere is no exception of aliants neither, as the<note n="a" place="margin">Lyra in Exod. <hi>22.</hi> Galat. de arca, Cathol. verit. l. <hi>11.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> Iewes themſelves confeſſe, &amp; our Saviour in the<note n="*" place="margin">Math 5.42. Luk. 6 35.</note> Goſpel taketh away that difference of bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and aliant, and of poore and rich too. And ſo in the prophet <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> and the <hi>Proverbs.</hi> For <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie</hi> by long experience in the Romane State did finde, that uſurie was<note n="b" place="margin">Liv. dec. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>damnoſiſsima etiam diviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus:</hi> and <hi>Plutarke</hi> avoucheth, that <hi>Jupiter Cteſius</hi> (ſo termed becauſe he is owner of all) can not ſave that man, that wil rather borrow upon uſurie, then ſell his owne goods to ſerve his turne.</p>
               <p>His fourth, and laſt evaſion is,<note place="margin">Defendor.</note> 
                  <hi>that the word tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated uſurie ſignifieth biting; ſo that if there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny uſurie which biteth not the poore, but healeth the bite, which the tooth of pouertie hath made, it cannot lie under the condemnation of this place.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is a great evaſion with uſurers,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> which they ſtand much upon: inſomuch that everie illiterate carle, and bookeleſſe broker hath <hi>Neſhech</hi> in his uncircumciſed mouth, and can ſay that <hi>Neſhech</hi> ſignifieth biting, &amp; therefore this Defendor tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlateth this place thus: <hi>Thou ſhalt not lay upon him a biting: as that word is knowne to ſignifie,</hi> ſaith he: But to fire them all out of this ſtarting hole at once, I tell them that this word <hi>Neſhech</hi> doth never ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie <hi>biting:</hi> nor any thing elſe but onely <hi>uſurie,</hi> that is, gaine for lending. If it be ſuch a knowne thing, as he maketh it, let him or any of them all ſhew one place in Canonicall Scripture, or other He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6252:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
writer, where <hi>Neſhech</hi> ſignifieth <hi>a biting,</hi> or any thing elſe, but onely that which the Hebrues with another name call <hi>Tarbith,</hi> the Greekes <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Latines <hi>foenus,</hi> and we <hi>uſurie.</hi> I haue beene ten yeeres Profeſſor of Hebrue in a famous Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and therefore ſhould haue read ſomewhat, and yet I confeſſe I could never finde it. The trueth is this; there are many Verbes in Hebrue, which in diuers Conjugations, or with divers conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or both, do ſignifie divers, yea ſometime con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary things: and therefore though they be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with the ſame letters, yet may well be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted divers Verbes, as<note n="a" place="margin">Theod. Gaza. Gram. lib. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Theodorus Gaza</hi> ſaith, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the like in the Greeke tongue. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>it is manifest that the</hi> ſame <hi>verbe being take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> divers waies,</hi> (or in divers ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifications) <hi>doth differ from it ſelfe in verie eſſence, and is diverſly called, and conſtrued.</hi> Yea in Hebrue ſome few of them in the ſame conjugation, and with the ſame conſtruction too, do ſignifie verie different things: which difference, and diverſitie in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall is diſcerned either by the Conjugation, or Conſtruction, or elſe by the circumſtances of the place: as the Verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which is uſed in the next verſe, in the conjugation <hi>Pihel</hi> ſignifieth <hi>to destroy, and diſſolve aſunder:</hi> but contrarily in <hi>Cal</hi> it ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>to binde together;</hi> whence commeth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>a cord, or cable</hi> which reteineth the Hebrue etymologie) and becauſe poſſeſſions and inheritances were uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally devided by corde, an inheritance is alſo called
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6252:28"/>
by the ſame name, <hi>Chebel.</hi> Now ſhall I ſay, becauſe this, or that mans landes were never laide out by cord, but other waies, therefore it is not inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <hi>Chebel;</hi> for <hi>Chebel</hi> ſignifieth <hi>a cord?</hi> much leſſe may I ſaie, that <hi>Neſhech</hi> ſignifieth <hi>biting,</hi> as anone ſhall appeare. Againe the ſame Verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>Cal</hi> ſignifieth to take to pledge, and a pledge is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Chabol,</hi> ſhall I ſay, that when God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth to take a milſtone to pledge, I may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully doe it, ſo there be no bond, or binding of it, for <hi>Chabal</hi> ſignifieth <hi>to binde?</hi> The Verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>Cal</hi> is taken Neutrally, and ſignifieth <hi>to kneele, and thence</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is <hi>a knee,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is a <hi>pond,</hi> belike becauſe that in ſwimming there, men bend their knees: as in Greeke ſuch a poole is called<note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 5.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a ſwimming place:</hi> Now becauſe in this, or that pond there was never any ſwimming, or a man cannot ſwimme in it becauſe of the ſhallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it, or ſome other cauſe; is it not therefore <hi>berechah, colymbethra, a pond?</hi> or ſhall I ſay, that thoſe words ſignifie ſwimming, or a ſwimming place? Againe, the ſame verbe <hi>barak</hi> in the conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation <hi>Piel</hi> is uſed tranſitively, and ſignifieth <hi>to bleſſe, or ſalute,</hi> becauſe uſually inferiours, bleſſing, or ſaluting their ſuperiors, did kneele or bow the knee, and thence <hi>barachab</hi> is a <hi>bleſsing, or ſaluting,</hi> and ſometime contrarily it ſignifieth to <hi>curſe, or ban.</hi> Shall I therefore ſay, that there is no bleſſing where there is no kneeling? or that <hi>barachah</hi> is knowne to ſignifie <hi>a kneeling?</hi> that<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 1.22.28.</note> God did not bleſſe his creatures, becauſe he did not kneele? that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:6252:29"/>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 103.</note> the heavens did not bleſſe God, becauſe they had no knees? that <hi>Jacob</hi> did not bleſſe his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 49.</note> becauſe he lay along in his bed? or when<note n="d" place="margin">Num. 23.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Balaam</hi> anſwered <hi>Balak</hi> that God had commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him to bleſſe Iſraell, <hi>and not to curſe,</hi> might <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lak</hi> have anſwered, notwithſtanding, thou art not forbidden to uſe ſorcerie, inchauntment, or witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft againſt them, ſo there be no kneeling, for that word is knowne to ſignifie kneeling? Or might <hi>Eſau</hi> have anſwered his Father <hi>Iſaak,</hi> that the ſame which his brother <hi>Iacob</hi> had ſtolen away, was not a bleſſing, becauſe <hi>Iſaak</hi> did not kneele. <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.37. <hi>Num.</hi> 21. Surely he might have anſwered ſo as truely, as our Uſurers ſay, that <hi>Neſhech</hi> ſignifieth <hi>biting.</hi> For although the verbe <hi>Neſhach</hi> uſed in <hi>Cal,</hi> tranſitively with an accuſative caſe of the ſufferer, ſignifieth <hi>to bite,</hi> as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Num. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>momor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit ſerpens virum; the Serpent did bite a man;</hi> yet in the conjugation <hi>Hiphil,</hi> (to which <hi>Neſhech</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and conſignificant) it requireth a dative caſe of the ſufferer, and an accuſative <hi>cognatae ſignificationis</hi> (as the Latin Gramarians ſpeake, the Greeke call them <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) and ſo it never ſignifieth <hi>to bite,</hi> but onely <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>foenerare, to uſurie</hi> (if you will give me leave to make a word (<hi>or to put to uſury</hi> as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Deut. 23.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Non foenerabis fratri tuo foenus: Thou ſhalt not uſurie to thy brother uſurie of ſilver.</hi> In which ſignification, or acceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is another verbe from that which ſignifieth <hi>to bite,</hi> differing from it in very eſſence, as <hi>Theodorus Gaza</hi> ſaid, which is more truely ſaide of this verbe, which differeth
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:6252:29"/>
from the other not onely in acception,<note place="margin">The Hebrue <hi>conjugata</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed verbatim without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of words, &amp; ſcarſe with that neither, for as in Greek the uſurer is ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> actively, and the uſer <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> depone<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo in He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall is ſaide <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trally, and the uſer <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as in Greeke <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp; the Uſurer <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, which is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>tranſiens in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium,</hi> as <hi>Chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chi</hi> ſaith which kinds of ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king our tongs cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe.</note> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, but alſo in conjugation; which in He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue maketh a great difference, as you may ſee by many examples: as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>Cal</hi> ſignifieth <hi>to redeeme,</hi> in <hi>Ptel, to pollute:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>Cal</hi> ſignifieth <hi>to create, or make;</hi> in <hi>Hiphil, to fatten:</hi> and ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>is fat:</hi> and the ſame verbe in <hi>Hiphil,</hi> alſo ſignifieth <hi>to chuſe;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in one, and the ſame conjugation <hi>Cal,</hi> with the prepoſitions <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or ſuch like ſignifieth <hi>to dwell: with</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>to feare, or to be afraid of:</hi> and an hundreth more of like ſort. And that <hi>Neſhech</hi> ſignifieth <hi>uſurie, and</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Naſhach, to goe to uſurie,</hi> without any reſpect of biting may appeare. <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.19. where it is applyed to the principall, or the things lent, <hi>of any thing, which doth uſurie, or goeth to uſurie.</hi> Now the thing lent be it money, meate, or whatſoever elſe doth never <hi>bite,</hi> but helpe and relieve: the intent of the lender is not to <hi>bite;</hi> the intent of the borrower is not to be <hi>bitten;</hi> the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the thing itſelfe is not biting; and therefore that word there cannot probably, or poſſibly be tranſlated, <hi>biting;</hi> and therefore <hi>Neſhech,</hi> and <hi>Hisſhech</hi> being <hi>conjugata</hi> to it, and Derivatives of it, ought not to be taken in the ſignification of <hi>bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting;</hi> but in the ſame ſignification, wherein their originall, &amp; primitive is; and what an abſurd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction would it be to tranſlate the derivatives in that ſort. <hi>Thou ſhalt not bite (or make to bite) to thy brother a biting of ſilver, or a biting of meate, &amp;c.</hi> What a ſenceleſſe ſpeech would this be? And for further confirmation, that the word <hi>Neſhech,</hi> and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:6252:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Naſhach</hi> doth import uſurie without any reſpect of <hi>biting,</hi> let me adde the judgement of the moſt skilfull in that tongue, who doe ever tranſlate, and expound it <hi>uſurie,</hi> without any mention, or inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation of <hi>biting,</hi> as the <hi>Septuaginta</hi> tranſlate it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>? The <hi>Chaldean Paraphraſt</hi> doth call it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ribbitha;</hi> The <hi>Rabbines</hi> expound it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which with them is the generall name of uſury. But grant that uſurie had his name in Hebrew of a Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, which ſignified <hi>biting,</hi> what is that to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, when we know what the thing is, which it is applyed to ſignifie? The queſtion is not of the <hi>Etymologie,</hi> but of the lawfulneſſe of the thing: the thing is knowne, what it is; whence the name was firſt take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that the ſame thing is called by, is not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall.<note n="a" place="margin">Ang. Princ. Dialect. c. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> giveth a very good rule. <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum non unde dictum ſit curandum, cum quid ſignificet intelligatur. It is no matter whence the word is deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, when we know the thing which it ſignifieth.</hi> In giving names to things, it is well enough, if the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which it hath <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as the <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines</hi> ſpeake) for the moſt part, be agreeable to it: yea if it ever had ſuch a qualitie which the name importeth, though the ſame qualitie, or accident be left, or growen out of uſe: as carnall copulation with a ſingle perſon is <hi>fornication</hi> ſtill, though it be not committed in <hi>an arched, or vanted roome;</hi> and yet that ſinne had his name firſt <hi>a fornice;</hi> as before hath beene ſhewed, becauſe then often it was committed in ſuch places, and therefore<note n="b" place="margin">Gallen. de H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>poc. &amp; Plat. decret. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> ſaide truely <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Etymologie is
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:6252:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
but a lying witneſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cic. in Topic.</note> which made <hi>Tullie</hi> ſo afraid to tranſlate <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>veriloqutum.</hi> Me thinkes I could helpe the Uſurers in this point better, then the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendor hath done: for therere is no uſurie, but that which <hi>accedit ſorti,</hi> as this Defendor ſaide truely before; but <hi>ſors</hi> importeth <hi>chance, hazard:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fortuitum rei eventum. Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pont.</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whether we lend to poore, or rich; gaine they, or gaine they not, if we put the principall out of hazard, and make it ſure by bond, ſuerty, or pawne, what increaſe ſoever we take, it is no <hi>uſurie, Quia non accedit ſorti; becauſe it commeth not to a thing put in hazard.</hi> Laſtly, grant that the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture condemned only <hi>biting</hi> of the poore, or bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of thy brother by lending; yet we might eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtand all uſurie to be forbidden, becauſe all uſurie <hi>biteth</hi> more, or leſſe, as one biting is worſe then another; and one ſooner felt than ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and therefore no marvaile that the moſt wiſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and name-maker linked their names in ſuch neere affinitie together. The biting of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, being done prively, when a man is aſleepe, or greatly buſied, is not great, nor ſoone felt, but it groweth; and if it continue, it will overrunne the whole body: and ſuch is the nature of uſurie, ſaith <hi>Rabbi Solomon:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rab. Solomon in Ezech. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>As the Serpent maketh a little blacke and blew in the foote, and there is no feeling of it, but afterward it groweth, and ſpreadeth it ſelfe, till it come over the crowne: So in uſurie, there is no feeling of it, no perceiving of it, till it grow great, and diminiſh a great deale of ſubſtance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The next place is Levit.</hi> 25.35.36.37.<note place="margin">Defendor.</note> 
                  <hi>Out of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:6252:31"/>
which place the ſame may be confirmed, and further reaſons gathered, for the ſtrengthning of the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment before ſet downe. Firſt, whatſoever is ſet downe, and forbidden to be done, is not forbidden generally, but to thy neighbour that is brought low.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note>This argument of our uſurie Defendor, <hi>vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God providing for a man that is decayed, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth to take uſurie of him, <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is lawfull to take uſurie of one that is not decayed, hath beene ſufficiently anſwered before. And further it may be ſaid here, that the commaundement of help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and upholding, verſe 35. belongeth to the brother decayed; but the commaundement for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding <hi>uſurie,</hi> verſe 36. pertayneth to the brother in generall, as well as <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.19. which ſeemeth to be inforced, becauſe in this 36. verſe he nameth the brother in generall. But it mattereth not much though both the commaundements be reſtrained onely to the brother decayed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Defendor.</note>
                  <hi>Secondly, there is a farther reaſon drawne from the end, which is, that thy brother may live with thee: wherefore if the loue of money be ſo tempered, that hee may well live with thee, it is plaine that ſuch uſurie is not forbidden.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note>Heere the uſurer diſcovereth his minde, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny rate of uſurie may be taken, ſo the poore bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower may live, and hold ſoule, and life together. And truely experience ſheweth,<note place="margin">Nec liberum corpus ſuperest. Liu. <hi>1.</hi> l. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> that uſurers have no more reſpect of their brethren: goods, landes, libertie, and all they get; and it is well that the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:6252:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
brother lives, <hi>&amp; veſcitur aura aetherea.</hi> But to his argument. Firſt theſe words <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>let thy brother live with thee</hi> (for ſo the text is, not as <hi>Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melius</hi> noteth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>that the life of thy brother may be with thee</hi>) are not the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or rule for the rate of uſurie, as this Defendor would have it, but an argument to moove us to leave it, taken from our dutie to our brother: as in the verſe next before, there is another argument to the ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, taken from our dutie towards God. By dutie we are bound to feare God. <hi>Ergo</hi> we muſt not take uſurie, becauſe God hath forbidden it: by dutie we are bound to preſerve, and maintaine the life of our neighbour: <hi>ergo,</hi> we muſt not take uſurie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe uſurie taketh from him that, wherewith he ſhould maintaine his life, his living, his goods. Whereby appeareth, that <hi>Catoes</hi> anſwer was not unreaſonable, when being demaunded what uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie was, anſwered<note n="a" place="margin">Quid ſoenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re? quid homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem occidere. Cic. offic. l. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>manſlaughter:</hi> And that <hi>Licinius</hi> complaint was not unjuſt,<note n="b" place="margin">Foenore truci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantur. Liv. Dec. <hi>1.</hi> l. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that men were ſlaine with uſurie.</hi> Now ſaith this Defendor, I may take uſurie ſo my brother <hi>may live:</hi> let him ſay alſo, I may take uſurie ſo I <hi>feare God;</hi> and then all uſurers wil be excuſed: for many of them counterfeit ſuch holineſſe, that they will be taken for men that feare God; and have ever the feare of God in their mouthes; for as a reverend father ſaid publikely of late, <hi>there are of our holiest brethren which are uſurers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, this is a bad conſequence: I muſt not take uſury of a decaied brother, who if he pay uſury cannot live, <hi>ergo,</hi> I may take uſurie of the rich, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:6252:32"/>
they may live notwithſtanding they pay uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Will the ſpeciall reaſon of a ſpeciall law, given in regard of ſome one circumſtance, abridge &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine the generall law? Will the exaggeration of a ſinne in the higheſt degree make all thoſe actions no ſinne, which come not to that degree? God forbiddeth a man, which hath bought an Iſraeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh maide, to ſell her to a ſtranger, giuing this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,<note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 21.7.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe he hath abuſed her:</hi> Was it therefore lawfull for ſuch a maſter to ſell an Iſraelitiſh maid, if he had not abuſed her? No,<note n="b" place="margin">Levit. 25.42.</note> that is unlawfull too. Becauſe it is an heinous offence to ſteale a cow from a man, that hath no more to live by: is it not a ſinne to ſteale a ſheepe from a man, that hath thouſands, and can live well enough for all that, and perhaps never miſſe it? The Defendor might have ſeene a more generall reaſon of the forbidding of uſurie in this place of <hi>Leviticus:</hi> for firſt, <hi>verſ.</hi> 37. he ſetteth downe a generall law: <hi>Thou ſhalt not give him</hi> (that is thy brother) <hi>thy money up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on uſurie, nor thy vittaile upon lone.</hi> Then <hi>verſ.</hi> 38. he giveth this reaſon, <hi>for I am the Lord thy God, which brought you</hi> (both the lender and the borrower) <hi>out of the land of Egypt.</hi> Now he brought the rich, as well as the poore out of the land of Egypt, and therfore neither rich nor poore (though they have no other way to live but by a ſtocke of money) may give their money upon uſurie either to rich, or poore.<note place="margin">Defendor.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly, for that the increaſe of victuals, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently of corne, is as well forbidden, as of money,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:6252:32"/>
wherefore corne ordinarily increaſing in theſe Countries</hi> 100. 60. 30. <hi>fold, if it be lawfull to take increaſe of corne, it is lawfull to take increaſe of money; But the former is not denied of ſome that are the greateſt ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of uſurie: And therfore, even in their judgement, if they will be like the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves the other may not be denied.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This propoſition <hi>it is lawfull to take increaſe of corne,</hi> is amphibologicall, and ambiguous:<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> if he meane, that it is lawfull for the husbandman to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the increaſe of his corne that he hath ſowed, as his mentioning of the increaſe of 100. fold doth import, it is moſt true; but it will never be fitted to our queſtion of uſurie: for there is no <hi>mutuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or lending,</hi> but metaphoricall. If he meane, that a man finding nothing but corne, and putting it to another to ſow to parts, may take his part of that which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of it; be it leſſe then he put out, or as much, or more; &amp; ſo if more, to take increaſe, it is alſo true, but it is nothing to uſurie; for it is plaine <hi>Societie.</hi> If he meane, that a man lending corne to another, and the borrower ſow the ſame, the lender may covenant with him to have his Principall againe, and ſome increaſe for the uſe; he muſt proue that true. For I deny it, and, untill he proue it, ſay it is unlawfull, becauſe it is uſurie. And yet this is nothing to that kind of increaſe, which is ſpoken of in this 37. verſe; for that is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>increaſe of food.</hi> And indeede it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth conſequently, that the forbidding the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of food, forbiddeth alſo the increaſe of corne borrowed to make foode of: but that differeth <pb n="56" facs="tcp:6252:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
much from corne ſowed for increaſe; which may be as well for marchandize, as for the ſowers ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Againe, with ſowing it hath an aptneſſe to increaſe naturally, which by ſowing <hi>reducitur ad actum:</hi> which aptneſſe ſpending corne, vitaile, and money hath not: for the making of that corne apt to ſpend, ſpoyleth it of his aptneſſe to increaſe. So here is a ſuite of <hi>non ſequiturs.</hi> Increaſe of victuall is forbidden: <hi>Ergo,</hi> increaſe of corne ſowed is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden. Corne ſowed increaſeth 100. fould: <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is lawfull to take uſurie of money: or, it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to take increaſe of corne ſowed: <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to take uſurie of money. What <hi>media</hi> will he have to tye theſe together?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Defendor.</note>
                  <hi>The lawfulneſſe whereof may appeare by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Ioſeph. Gen.</hi> 47.13. <hi>Who for foode once given, tooke a fift for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note>The Relative <hi>(whereof)</hi> is referred by him to the increaſe of corne, as I take it, not to the increaſe of money. So the argument is this. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> for food once given tooke a fift for ever; <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is lawfull to take increaſe of corne; and conſequently of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. I anſwere, firſt the <hi>Antecedent</hi> is falſe. It was not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>foode,</hi> nor <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>frumentum, bread-corne,</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſeede, or ſeede-corne</hi> that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> gave the Aegyptians, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſheweth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.23. Againe <hi>Ioſephs</hi> contract, and bargaine was not to have his Principall againe, and increaſe beſides, as in uſurie is requiſite: but the Principall was transferred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way for ever by that contract, in conſideration of that fift part; which is contrary to <hi>mutuating, and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:6252:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
lending.</hi> Laſtly, he did not onely give them ſeede, but alſo did let them land to ſow it upon, and to occupie withall; elſe their ſeede without lande would have done them no good: for lande they had none, unleſſe they farmed it of <hi>Pharao:</hi> for <hi>Joſeph</hi> had<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 47.20.</note> bought all their land for <hi>Pharao,</hi> and had<note n="b" place="margin">21.</note> put them cleane out of poſſeſſion; ſo they tooke land againe in<note n="c" place="margin">24.</note> farme; and afterward by ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute it was graunted unto them<note n="d" place="margin">26.</note> in fee-farme, and they became <hi>Emphytentae, fee-farmers</hi> to <hi>Pharao.</hi> Now letting of land in fee-farme will be a ſlender patronage of putting of money, victual, or corne to uſurie. This conſequence will never be proved: <hi>Joſeph</hi> did let to the Egyptians land with a ſtocke of corne with it in fee-farme, <hi>ergo</hi> it is lawful to put corne, victuall, and money to uſurie. And marke his corollarie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Out of which place it further appeareth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Defendor.</note> 
                  <hi>how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groundedly out of</hi> Ariſtotle <hi>the increaſe upon lone of money is condemned as unnaturall, becauſe, forſooth, money begetteth not money; whereas the Scripture con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth indifferently the increaſe of foode, as well as of money: for notwithſtanding it increaſeth not, yet being well, and wiſely imploied, turned and returned, it cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth greater increaſe than other things which are lent, which without imployment, and manuring will bring no increaſe; no not the ground it ſelfe of other commodities the beſt and ſurest.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Indeed out of this ſpeech it appeareth how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groundedly <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> this Defendor ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth, and reaſoneth: heere is his argument in the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:6252:34"/>
beſt faſhion that I can bring it into: God condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the increaſe of vittaile, as well as of money: but vittaile though it doe not increaſe of it ſelfe, or lying ſtill, yet being imploied it doth increaſe, and that increaſe is lawfull to be taken; <hi>ergo,</hi> money though not increaſing it ſelfe, yet being well, and wiſely imploied, turned, and returned, it cauſing increaſe, that increaſe likewiſe is lawfull to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. I denie in his antecedent that vittaile doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, for I cannot deviſe how it can, unleſſe it be by miracle, as the woman of <hi>Sareptaes</hi> meale, and oile; or as the Diſciples loaves and fiſhes: for vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall hath no aptneſſe to increaſe, no more then money hath. How long ſhall a man keepe a loafe or bread, a gallon of Beere, a pound of Butter, or Cheeſe, a ſtone of Mutton, or Beefe before it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe? or what may he do to it to make it increaſe? If he meane that the victuler maketh increaſe, and gaine by uttering his victual, that muſt be by ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, which contract he cannot make of money; for money is the price, which<note n="a" place="margin">Eccleſ. 10.19.</note> 
                  <hi>anſwereth to all;</hi> and therefore cannot be the ware, and merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize too. If he meane of corne; indeed that hath a vegetative, augmentative, and increaſing nature, apt to increaſe; but being turned to victuall, and made edible, as parched, ſodden, grinded, it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived, and ſpoiled of that nature, and aptneſſe. If he meane of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſeed-corne,</hi> he is cleane beſide the law, and out of the queſtion; neither wil his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon hold: for money hath not in it naturallie ſuch an aptneſſe to increaſe, as all kinde of ſeede
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:6252:34"/>
hath: doe what you can to money, you cannot make that increaſe, or more to grow of it, unleſſe it be by <hi>Alcumie,</hi> which they call the arte of Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication: and whether it be lawful to take increaſe for money put to the <hi>Alcumiſts,</hi> I leave to them which know the virtue of the <hi>Philoſophers ſtone,</hi> and haue skill in that arte. But without <hi>Alcumie</hi> I am ſure it cannot be. Well more money may be added to it, but that <hi>more</hi> never came of it, or grew of it: for it hath no <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>potentiam, facultie,</hi> apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or nature to increaſe, or to yeeld a profite, and commodity beſides the thing, as ground hath, which he produceth for example: but how wiſely a blinde man may ſee: for who did ever lende or mutuate ground? Ground, becauſe it hath a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall aptneſſe to yeeld profit, and commoditie, ſo that the uſe may be ſevered from the thing, may be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modated; &amp; conſequently, ſomething being paid for that uſe, it may be hired. Now ſuch a uſe there cannot be of money, as money; of gold, as gold; of ſilver, as ſiluer, perhaps there may be; but not of coine, or money. And if there be any ſuch uſe, which may be transferred to the borrower, the propertie remaining in the lender, it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth not within our queſtion, or the contract of <hi>mutua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</hi> Now heere our Defendor produceth two excellent properties of money.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Defendor.</note> 
                  <hi>money hath a propertie of continuance with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out danger of periſhing, which cattell, and other things ſubject to death, and diſeaſes have not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Saviour Chriſt telleth us otherwiſe;<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> whom <pb n="60" facs="tcp:6252:35"/>
this Defendor, be he never ſo great, and learned a man, muſt give me leave rather to credit. For de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting us from the treaſuring up of earthly trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures (whereof coine is no ſmall part) he uſeth one argument taken from the nature of it, ſubject of it ſelfe to corruption,<note n="a" place="margin">Math. 6.28.</note> namely to ruſt. And S. <hi>Iames</hi> telleth us plainly, that ſilver and gold are ſubject to ruſt, and canker:<note n="b" place="margin">Jam. 5.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Your gold, and ſilver is canke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the ruſt of them ſhall be a witneſſe against you.</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Math. 6.28.</note> Another argument is taken from the danger of them, becauſe they are ſubject to ſtealing, not onely if a man carry them in his purſe, or keepe them in a cheſt; but even if he wall them within a ſtone wall. <hi>The theeues digge through, and ſteale.</hi> And<note n="d" place="margin">Act. 8.</note> S. <hi>Peter</hi> telleth <hi>Simon Magus, Thy money pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh with thee.</hi> Therefore he did not thinke that money was not ſubject <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>to periſhing,</hi> as this Defendor doth. Now compare it to cattell, and it is farre inferiour in the propertie of continuance. For though cattell be ſubiect to diſeaſes, &amp; death too: yet they are by nature <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>aucti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficous, and multiplicative,</hi> and therefore leave other in their roome behinde them; whereby they have indeede a propertie of continuance, and almoſt of perpetuitie. But graunt that money had ſuch a propertie of continuance without danger of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing; is it therefore lawfull to take uſury for len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of it? Why, who borroweth money to keepe it continually, or to hoord it up? Or who is ſo madde as to pay uſurie for this uſe, and propertie of it? The poore uſer or borrower cares for no
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:6252:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
more, then if it will laſt telling it to his Creditor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſecond propertie of it is;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Defendor.</note> 
                  <hi>that having money there is no commoditie which a man may not have: ſo that though money be barren in one reſpect, yet it is more fruitfull than other commodities in regard of a greater and an oftner burden it is delivered off to the comfort of them, that know how to uſe it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, this is not generally true;<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> as the Spaniards found by experience, who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming into the Weſt Indies, had many commodities of the Countrie, which they needed, brought unto them by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants: to whom they would offer for them mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, goodly pieces of golde coine, but the Indians taking the money, would put it into their mouths, and ſpit it out to the Spaniards againe, ſignifying that they could not eate it, or make uſe of it; and therefore would not part with their commodities for money, unleſſe they had ſuch other commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as would ſerue their uſe. Secondly though money commonly bee the meane for all commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, and do anſwere to all; yet this uſe of money cannot be ſeuered from the thing it ſelfe, that wee may make that uſe of it, and keepe the thing, or the propertie in the thing too. For indeed it is the very right uſe of money, and this uſe of it, is the ſpending of the very thing: and therefore can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bee made of that thing but once; for money cannot be ſpent twiſe, nor be twiſe delivered of yong, ſaue onely in Uſurie: which kinde of birth, if he meane here, when hee ſpeaketh of the great and often burthen, which money is delivered of,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:6252:36"/>
he doeth but <hi>principium petere:</hi> for the lawfulneſſe of that kind of birth, is the thing in queſtion. Now then the uſe of money being the ſpending of the thing, ſhall I make euen, and equall recompence for the thing, and give for the uſe beſide? Noe, but one thing anſwereth to both, they both being but one thing, and not ſeverable. Becauſe a pot of beere hath a propertie to coole thirſt; ſhall I give a pot of beere againe for the beere I borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſomewhat beſide for the propertie of it, to coole my thirſt? Becauſe ten pounds in money wil buy a horſe worth ten pounds, muſt I anſwere ten pounds for the money, and ten ſhillings more for the propertie of the money to buy a horſe? This is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort which the Defendor ſpeaketh of,<note place="margin">Job 16.2.</note> 
                  <hi>A mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable comforter are you,</hi> may the poore borrower ſay.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Defendor.</note>
                  <hi>Now where in this text verſ.</hi> 36. <hi>There is beſide the word of biting, another word which ſignifieth increaſe in the</hi> 37. <hi>verſe, it is evident that the worde of biting was aſcribed to the money, and the word of increaſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to the food. So that they doe euidently force the words of this place, which apply the worde of increaſe unto money, which is here by the holy Ghoſt carried onely unto food. Wherefore alſo the Prophets being interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Law, it followeth that the places of Ezech.</hi> 18. <hi>and Proverb.</hi> 28. <hi>where both theſe words are uſed of biting, and multiplying: ought to be ſo expounded, as the biting be referred to the money, and the worde of multiplication to the food, or victuals, and not to money as is commonly done. If the holy Ghoſt had in any place
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:6252:36"/>
forbidden the increaſe of money, as he forbiddeth the biting of the brother in all things, as well money, as vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals; then there had beene reaſon to have applied the increaſe to money, but the Scripture not forbidding that any where, it is an over-reach ſo to apply it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This evaſion is both untrue, and alſo idle,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> and unable to doe him good. It is untrue, that it is an over-reach to apply <hi>Tarbith</hi> to money, or that <hi>Tarbith</hi> is reſtrained onely to victuall. For the worde which the holie Ghoſt <hi>verſ.</hi> 37. carieth expreſly to victuall, is not <hi>Tarbith,</hi> as he belying the holie Ghoſt telleth us; but <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bith,</hi> which is a worde of more generall ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, applied to<note n="a" place="margin">1. Sam. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>iſſue of body, increaſe of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">2. Chron. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>increaſe of wiſedome,</hi> and ſo foorth. But the word <hi>Tarbith</hi> which is uſed <hi>verſ.</hi> 36. and <hi>Prov.</hi> 28. and <hi>Ezech.</hi> 18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22. is the proper name of uſurie, and ſignifieth nothing elſe: ſo that <hi>Tarbith,</hi> and <hi>Neſhech</hi> be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (as the Hebrues call them) that is <hi>Synonyma, words of one ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> though they differ in <hi>Etymologie,</hi> and originati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: as the Latin <hi>uſura,</hi> and <hi>foenus</hi> be: which though the one come of <hi>faetus,</hi> the other of <hi>uſus,</hi> yet ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie one, and the ſame thing, which we call uſury: as appeareth in <hi>Tully,</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Cic. de Senect.</note> 
                  <hi>terra nunquam ſine uſura red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit quod accepit; ſed aliàs minore, plaerumque majore cum faenore:</hi> and ſo we have in Engliſh <hi>uſe, and lone.</hi> And this is a uſuall figure in Hebrue, as their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors often note <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>to dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the thing with two wordes.</hi> And that <hi>Tarbith</hi> and <hi>Neſhech</hi> be <hi>Synonyma</hi> may appeare by many rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:6252:37"/>
Firſt whereas in this place <hi>Moſes</hi> reſtraineth <hi>Neſhech</hi> to money; yet <hi>Deutr.</hi> 23.19. he ſtretcheth it to victuall alſo; which argueth that <hi>Neſhech</hi> is generally of all things as well as of money. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the Chaldaean Paraphraſt, when <hi>Neſhech,</hi> and <hi>Tarbith</hi> be put together, as he tranſlateth <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bith</hi> alwaies <hi>ribbitha,</hi> which come both of one Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative, haue one etymon, and are one word dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering onely in <hi>Dialect,</hi> but <hi>Neſhech</hi> he tranſlateth ſometimes <hi>Chibbulja,</hi> ſometime <hi>Nuchtetha:</hi> yet <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.19. he tranſlateth <hi>Neſhech</hi> alſo <hi>Ribbitha:</hi> ſhewing plainely, that he tooke <hi>Tarbith</hi> to be the ſame which <hi>Neſhech</hi> is, and as generall as it, and of money as well as it: for <hi>Ribbitha,</hi> and <hi>Tarbith</hi> dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in nothing but in dialect. Thirdly, as the Verbe ſignifying <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>foenerare,</hi> to put to uſurie, in He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue is conjugatum to <hi>Neſhech:</hi> ſo in Chaldaean, which is but a dialect of the Hebrue, it is conjuga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum to <hi>Tarbith,</hi> which maketh them plaine Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymaes. Fourthly the Hebrue Doctors make them Synonyma, &amp; ſay <hi>Tarbith</hi> is the ſame which <hi>Neſhech</hi> is, as <hi>Mordochai Nathan</hi> in his <hi>Iair Nathib</hi> ſaith, <hi>Tarbith</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>the ſame which Neſhechis.</hi> Fiftly, the <hi>Septuagint</hi> doe alwaies tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate <hi>Neſhech</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <hi>Tarbith</hi> are al one, and have one and the ſame reaſon of their Etymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, as before hath beene ſhewed. And ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe doth the vulgar Latine tranſlation tranſlate <hi>Neſhech</hi> ſometime <hi>uſuram,</hi> and ſometime <hi>foenus:</hi> Now <hi>faenus</hi> alſo is all one with <hi>Tarbith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nonn. Marcel. de propr. Serm.</note> and hath the ſame reaſon of the Etymologie, being ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:6252:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>quia foetus est mutui accepti;</hi> and ſo is <hi>Tarbith,</hi> as before hath beene ſhewed. Sixtly, there can be no reaſon given why <hi>Tarbith</hi> ſhould be attributed to victuall, but by the ſame reaſon it may be attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to money: for the nature of victuall, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in this reſpect is all one, and the one doth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>parere, increaſe,</hi> as well as the other; both naturally unfruitefull, and barren; in uſurie both made to yeeld fruit contrarie to nature: the dammage to the borrower in both alike. For what oddes whether I lend you ten pound of butter to have as much againe, &amp; one pound over for lone: or lend you ten groats in money to buy it withall, to have as much money againe, and one pound of butter over, or one groat over for the lone: and ſo for all other kinde of victuals. And this evenneſſe, and equalitie in the nature of the things (namely that increaſe is alike lawful, or unlawfull in the one as in the other) the Defendor himſelfe confeſſeth. For ſeeing by his own conſtruction that <hi>Marbith,</hi> increaſe above the principall lent, is directly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden even in victuall, he commeth in with his old limitation, and qualification, <hi>ſo it be ſuch as doth not oppreſſe him, but relieue him:</hi> which is the ſelfe-ſame limitation, and qualification with which uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of money is alowed by him: &amp; without which the uſurie of money is condemned by him. So that howſoever he would bleare the eies of the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant with a diſtinction of the wordes, yet he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the things all one, that is, alike lawfull, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull; and ſo indeed maketh his goodly diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:6252:38"/>
meerely void, and vaine. Now to proove that the increaſe of victuall ſo qualified is lawfull, he uſeth this argument.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Defendor.</note>
                  <hi>The word which is termed increaſe ſignifieth multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, which is not alwaies where more is taken then was given, but where much is given: it being more to multiply then to increaſe, as appeareth,</hi> Deut. 17.16. <hi>where it being forbidden to the King to multiply hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, yet thereby is not forbidden, that the King ſhould have many horſes, but that he ſhould not exceede and goe beyond meaſure. For it is manifeſt, that the good and religious Kings in their great victories againſt the Churches enimies, having many horſes, reſerved ſome for their owne uſe. And therefore if ſuch an increaſe of victuals be taken as the poore may well live of, I ſee not how it is ſimplie unlawfull. Where alſo may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called backe againe the example of the Egyptians, which albeit they were brought to extreme povertie, yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived corne for the yeelding of an annuall increaſe for ever: and that at the hands of</hi> Ioſeph, <hi>which gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the land in juſtice, and was beneficiall to all the ſubjectes of the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note>All the copies of this booke, which I have ſeene, have <hi>(when more is given)</hi> but I take his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to be, when more is taken, that is, over-much, and exceſſiue: which appeareth to be his meaning, both by his compariſon, that to multiplie is more than to increaſe, and alſo by his teſtimonie allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged out of <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. Now this acception, and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which the holy Ghoſt uſeth, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. and whereof <hi>Tarbith</hi> is derived, is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:6252:38"/>
For it doth not import an exceſſe, or mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplication beyond meaſure, but an increaſe in any meaſure, that is, more than that, which it is compared with-all, be it it-ſelfe, or another thing; For it is oppoſite to <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>leſſe;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is <hi>more,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is <hi>leſſe:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>to grow more, or increaſe,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>to grow leſſe, or decreaſe:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>to make more:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>to make leſſe:</hi> as you may ſee, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.18. <hi>Num.</hi> 26.54. <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.6. and other places, where there is a bare compariſon made by theſe wordes, without any reſpect of exceſſe any way. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when an exceſſe beyond meaſure is ſignified, the word is either doubled, as <hi>in multiplying I will multiplie. Gen.</hi> 3.16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22.17. or elſe ſome word of exceſſe is added: as in this place <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>valde, over much, or exceedingly,</hi> verſe 17. which <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is to bee underſtood in the reſt, according to the exigence of the circumſtances; elſe abſurdities would follow. This place yeeldeth rather argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes againſt his aſſertion, then anything in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of it. As firſt,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.2.</note> God forbiddeth to multiply wives: but all increaſe of wives is unlawfull aboue his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>his owne one: Ergo,</hi> God forbidding <hi>Marbith,</hi> increaſe of victuals; all increaſe of victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als is unlawfull above his owne Principall. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the Verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>harbeh, to increaſe, or mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplie</hi> is attributed to money, <hi>Ergo,</hi> the nowne <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bith</hi> which is <hi>conjugatum</hi> to it, is attributed to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. And this may ſtand for a ſeaventh argument, to prove that <hi>Tarbith</hi> is a <hi>ſynonyma</hi> to <hi>Neſhech,</hi> and is of money, as well as of victuall.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:6252:39"/>Secondly, his evaſion is idle, and would doe him no good. For graunt that this diſtinction of his were true, that in the phraſe of <hi>Moſes</hi> the word <hi>Tarbith</hi> were reſtrained onely to that one kind of uſurie which was in victuall, and never uſed for that kinde which was in money, what would he get by it? Surely if <hi>Tarbith</hi> had never beene mentioned, the law of uſury had not beene one whit inlarged; and being mentioned, it is not one ace abated, or reſtrained: for the word <hi>Neſhech</hi> is large, forcible, and effectuall enough againſt uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, as before hath beene ſhewed. And ſo for his recalling backe the example of the Aegyptians to this purpoſe, I deſire the reader to remember what hath beene ſaid of it before.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Defendor.</note>
                  <hi>In</hi> Deuteronomie 23.19. <hi>he forbiddeth to lend to uſurie generally to any Jew, but there expreſly in all thoſe interdictes he uſeth the word of</hi> biting <hi>onely; a thing which is confeſſed ſimply unlawfull to be uſed to any man at any time, which is alſo the anſwere to the place of</hi> Pſal. 15. <hi>where the word</hi> biting <hi>is alſo uſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note>This is no good anſwere, for the word doth not ſignifie <hi>biting,</hi> but onely uſurie, as before hath beene ſhewed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Defendor.</note>
                  <hi>There followeth</hi> Ezech. 18.8.13.17. <hi>In all which places the generall which is forbidden is the oppreſsion of the poore: of which generall, this is one ſpeciall of</hi> biting, <hi>and</hi> multiplication: <hi>the one, as hath been ſaid, by money, the other by victuals, and other thinges. Wherefore if uſurie be ſo tempered, and qualified that it oppreſſe not the poore; it is plaine that it is not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:6252:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in that place: much leſſe if it be ſo meaſured as it doth greatly comfort, and relieve him. Moreover, as he forbiddeth uſurie there, ſo doth he in like degree for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid the retaining of a pledge for debt. Wherefore if there may be ſuch a debtor, whoſe Creditor may keepe the pledge laid downe with him, untill he be ſatisfied of the debt: there may be alſo ſuch a borrower, as the lender may without breach of the law take lone of him. But the former of theſe two is confeſſed, therefore the later cannot be denied.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Uſurie is not a <hi>ſpecies</hi> of any thing going before in that place of <hi>Ezechiel.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> Neither is oppreſſion of the poore any <hi>genus</hi> there. In the 8. <hi>verſe</hi> there goeth next before it the exerciſe of liberalitie in feeding the hungrie, and cloathing the naked; whereto Uſurie is an enimie, and therefore next forbidden: and next after it followeth committing of iniquitie, and not executing true judgement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene man, and man: which in the 8. <hi>verſe</hi> are coupled with it, and which may be done to other than to the poore. In the 13. <hi>verſe</hi> he puts it next to Idolatrie, and abomination: and therefore he cannot make Uſurie a <hi>ſpecies</hi> of the oppreſſion of the poore, unleſſe he make them ſo too. But this evaſion hath before beene anſwered; and ſo have his other evaſions of <hi>biting,</hi> &amp; keeping of a pledge.</p>
               <p>Proverb. 28.8.<note place="margin">Defendor.</note> 
                  <hi>He that increaſeth his ſubſtance by</hi> biting <hi>(which muſt be vnderſtood through money, as before hath beene ſhewed) or by multiplication (which muſt be underſtood by victuals, or ſuch like, as there alſo is ſet downe) ſhall gather it for him, that will
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:6252:40"/>
ſhew grace to the poore. Which if it be the true expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of this place, the uſurie before defended remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſtill untouched. But if this expoſition be not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; then the latter end of the</hi> verſe, <hi>which is an expoſition of the former part thereof, declareth, that this is to be ment of ſuch as take increaſe of the poore, &amp; oppreſſe them by lending. For the Proverbe ſeemeth not obſcurely to ſet foorth this ſence; that that which hath beene by a wicked covetous man taken away from the poore, ſhall be by a righteous liberall man reſtored to the poore againe. Thirdly, it muſt be obſerved, that this Proverbe, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note>His diſtinction of <hi>Tarbith,</hi> and <hi>Neſhech,</hi> which himſelfe doubteth of, and diſtruſteth here, hath beene anſwered before. His other evaſion, <hi>that the later part of the verſe is an expoſition of the former,</hi> is contrarie to the rules of interpretation; for the one containeth the ſinne, and the other the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And it is but a ſhallow conceite, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced conſtruction, that the Uſurer got his goods of the poore, becauſe his ſucceſſor will beſtow them upon the poore; whereas <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaketh generally. <hi>He that increaſeth his riches by uſurie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Defendor.</note>
                  <hi>Thirdly, it muſt be obſerved, that the Proverbe ſpeaketh of him, whoſe trade is to gaine by uſurie, and whoſe great wealth riſeth no other way then from thence, and ſo conſequently is without the compaſſe of that uſurie, which by the anſwere to the queſtion is maintained.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note>Though the Defendor ſay it muſt be, I thinke it may not be. For the Proverbe ſaith onely <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:6252:40"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>He that increaſeth, or augmenteth his ſubſtance, or maketh it more.</hi> Now if a man hath gotten 10000. pounds by other waies, and taken but 10. pounds, or 10. ſhillings for uſurie once in his life, doubtles he doth thereby increaſe &amp; augment his ſubſtance ſo much, and make it ſo much more; and therefore comes within the condemnation of this ſentence, though he make no occupation of uſurie, nor have any great wealth ariſing by it. But I marveile, what is in the foreſaid anſwere, to ſhut out him whoſe trade is to gaine by uſurie, out of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe thereof. For truely I can ſee nothing there, but, ſo that I lend onely to the rich, to purchaſe or compaſſe great matters withall, he may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully make a trade of it, and have his greateſt wealth ariſing by it.</p>
               <p>There is one place more in the olde Teſtament from which <hi>M.C.</hi> gathereth an argument to proue the lawfulneſſe of uſurie, as a thing in his owne nature indifferent; namely, <hi>Ier.</hi> 15.10. which he produceth in his anſwere to the fift queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which queſtion being the laſt, containeth an objection againſt the lawfulneſſe of borrowing upon uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, in theſe words. <hi>Laſtly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">M. C.</note> 
                  <hi>when the Prophet</hi> Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie <hi>ſaith, I have neither lent upon uſurie, nor any hath lent to me upon uſurie, and yet they curſe me, whether the word uſurie expreſſed there twiſe, have one and the ſame ſence and ſignification in either pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or in the firſt place to be taken in evill part, but not in the ſecond.</hi> To this <hi>M.C.</hi> anſwereth thus: <hi>The roote of the word in both places is one, and the ſame,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:6252:41"/>
and in neither place taken in evill part, neither in the ſignification of lending upon uſurie; nor in the ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of borrowing upon uſurie, but is of a thing indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent of it ſelfe. And it is ſo farre, that that place doth make any thing againſt the lawfulneſſe of uſurie, that it rather giveth ſome ſtrength to it. For the Prophet declareth his injurie to be ſo great, that he did not give them any cauſe, nay not ſo much as any occaſion juſtly to hate him; conſidering that he did abſtaine from that, which was not ſimply unlawfull: whereas if to lend, or borrow upon uſurie had beene ſimply un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, their unreaſonableneſſe had not ſo greatly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this anſwere M. <hi>C.</hi> bewrayeth ſome want of skill in the Originall tongue. For the word which the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> uſeth, doth never ſignifie <hi>Vſury,</hi> or <hi>Vſurarious contract;</hi> but is quite another thing: and therefore his indifferencie of the practiſe of u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurie cannot be prooued, or holpen by that. The interpretation of the place is: <hi>I did not credit them, nor they did credit me.</hi> But it was not ſuch a kind of creditor, and debtor, crediting, and owing, which is uſuall amongſt us, and according to the courſe of our law: but ſuch a creditor <hi>cui acquirebatur jus in bona debitoris: which had acquired, and gotten a right unto the goods of the debtor,</hi> that he might ſeize the ſame to his proper uſe, and detaine them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further courſe of law (for ſo much as I can find in the Iewes <hi>judicialls</hi>) but onely of his owne au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, &amp;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> handfaſting, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Deut.</hi> 15. till he were ſatisfied his debt. So it was not in
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:6252:41"/>
the nature of an execution, whereby the thing is transferred to the Creditor abſolutely, without li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to the debtor to redeeme it: neither in the nature of a bare debt, by which with us the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor hath no right to the debtors goods; neither of an arreſt, or diſtreſſe which requireth a courſe of law, and yet doth not transferre the property, or uſe of the thing preſently to the Creditor; but it is a thing of another nature, after the Iudiciall law of that ſtate, whereby the Creditor had au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to take any of the goods of the Debtors for his debt, and to detaine the ſame till he was ſatisfied; onely provided that the Creditor might not draw latch, or enter into the Debtors houſe to take what he thought good;<note place="margin">Deut. 24.10.12.13.</note> but to take ſuch as the Debtor could, and would ſpare: and alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, that if it were the onely garment of a poore man, he reſtored it to him when he needed it to cover his nakedneſſe. Such a Creditor is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> whom the Prophets wife feared would come and ſeize her two ſonnes:<note place="margin">2. Reg. 4.7.</note> Wherefore <hi>Eliſha</hi> furniſhed her with Oyle to ſell and ſatisfie him.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 22.2.</note> And in danger of ſuch Creditors ſtood the men that fled to <hi>David:</hi> and ſuch a debt was to be remitted in the yeere of <hi>Jubilie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 15.</note> the Creditors being forbidden to touch, or ſeize the Debtor, or his goods. And ſuch a kinde of credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the poore is againſt the law of charitie, and overthroweth the office of <hi>mutuating, or lending,</hi> and therefor prohibited by God, as well as uſurie. <hi>If thou lend money unto my people</hi> (I meane) <hi>to the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 22.25.</note>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:6252:42"/>
                  <hi>poore with thee, thou ſhalt not be to him as a Creditor.</hi> Not meaning a plaine Creditor, for that muſt he be, ſo long as the other was in his debt, and did owe him the thing lent; but ſuch a Creditor as I have deſcribed.<note place="margin">Nehem 5.7.</note> And therefore <hi>Nehemias</hi> condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it in the rich Iewes, and commaundeth releaſe therof both in reſtoring the goods ſeized,<note place="margin">10.11.3.4.</note> as <hi>lands, Vine-yardes, Olive-yardes, houſes:</hi> as alſo in remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the debt, were it money, or wares, as <hi>Corne, Wine, Oyle,</hi> which appeareth before to be the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for which they grew in debt. And by this ſhort diſcourſe the Defendor alſo may ſee his error, who maketh <hi>Noſheh,</hi> to be all traffique and negatiation; whereas it is but one kinde of crediting, as hath been deſcribed, the debtor whereof <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>oba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratus</hi>) is called <hi>periphraſtico<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Out of the newe Teſtament there is alleaged one place, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.35. where our Saviour exhorteth to Chriſtian liberalitie toward thoſe that want, and to true brotherly love, whoſe nature is in her benefites to reſpect the good of other,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.4.</note> 
                  <hi>not her owne:</hi> and for that part thereof which conſiſteth in mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuating, or lending, our Saviour ſetteth downe the rule thus (as S. <hi>Mathew</hi> recordeth it) <hi>And from him that would borrow of thee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 6.42.</note> 
                  <hi>turne not away:</hi> expreſſing the ſame, which <hi>Moſes</hi> in his rule for mutuating delivereth thus,<note place="margin">Deut. 15.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Let not thy eye be evill againſt thy brother.</hi> S. <hi>Luke</hi> ſetteth the rule downe thus: <hi>lend</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: now <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is not red in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place of the Newe Teſtament, and in other Greeke writers it ſignifieth <hi>to be in wan-hope,</hi> or <hi>out
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:6252:42"/>
of hope,</hi> with an accuſative caſe, as is here, as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to be out of hope of the ſicke man, or to deſpaire of the ſicke man.</hi> In which ſence if we take it here, it ſeemeth that our Saviour reſpecteth that wan-hope, or deſpaire of the principall in regard of the neereneſſe of the yeere of freedome, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there was to be a plaine <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and generall releaſe of all debts, which deſpaire <hi>Moſes</hi> in his rule of mutuating mentioneth: <hi>Beware that there be no wicked thought</hi> (of deſpairing thy debt) <hi>in thee, that thou ſhouldeſt ſay, the ſeaventh yeere is at hand, the yeere of freedome, therefore it grieveth thee to looke on thy poore brother, and lend him nothing.</hi> Which yeere of freedome, when our Saviour ſpake this, was at hand, as I have ſhewed in my booke of the ground of Chronologie. But the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretors doe take this word here in another ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, in which elſe-where it is never read, in this ſence, <hi>lend, hoping for nothing of them:</hi> ſo that the prepoſition <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſeemeth to be taken out of the verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the former verſe, <hi>and if you lend</hi> to them, <hi>whom you hope to receive of.</hi> Now what was that, which our Saviour would not have them to hope for of the borrower? The Principall? or the like kindneſſe in pleaſuring them with lending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, or ſuch offices, when they had neede? Not the Principall, as I take it, for theſe reaſons. Firſt, becauſe then it ſhould not be lending, but giving. Now our Saviour doth diſtinguiſh theſe two evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently: <hi>Give to him that asketh;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 6.42.</note> 
                  <hi>and from him that would borrow turne not away:</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Mathew. Give
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:6252:43"/>
to every one that asketh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 6.35.</note> 
                  <hi>and lend hoping for nothing,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Luke.</hi> The difference of theſe two is, that in giving, the thing is quite transferred away, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reſtoring of it againe, or hoping for it: in lending, the thing transferred away is to be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againe. Secondly, in the ende of the former verſe, in the example of the thing forbidden, there is expreſſed what it is, which in lending, we may not hope to receive, namely, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>the like.</hi> Now the Principall is not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>the like;</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the ſame <hi>in ſpecie,</hi> as before hath beene ſhewed. For <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> importeth the requiting the kindneſſe and good turne, in dooing the like againe. For that which the Latines ſay <hi>par pari referre, to doe him as good a turne:</hi> the Greekes ſay <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; ſuch an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Col. 4.1.</note> 
                  <hi>or requiting, Paule</hi> would have Maſters yeeld their ſervants, that they requite their dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and faithfulneſſe with due wages, and kindneſſe. Thirdly, the relation of the other Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian offices here expreſſed by our Saviour doth import ſo much: <hi>If you love them which love you; if you doe good to them which doe good to you,</hi> and ſo, <hi>if you lend to them of whom yee hope to receive the like,</hi> that is, which lend to you: and proportionably in the preceptes; <hi>love your enemies,</hi> which love you not; <hi>doe good to them,</hi> which doe not good to you: <hi>lend to them,</hi> which lend not to you. This ſence of this place doth utterly overthrow uſurie. For if in lending we muſt not reſpect, or expect <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the like good turne againe of the borrower; much leſſe may we compact for uſurie. For uſurie is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:6252:43"/>
                  <hi>more,</hi> which is contrarie to <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in the exceſſe: and he which forbiddeth the like, doth rather for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid that which is more. Now let us ſee what he ſaith againſt it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This place maketh as little againſt uſurie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Defendor.</note> 
                  <hi>as that which doth leaſt. For, Firſt of all our Saviour ſpeaketh not at all of any negotiation, or contractes for gaine, but onely of relieving the poore, as appeareth in the</hi> 30. verſe.</p>
               <p>It is true that he ſpeaketh not of any negotiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or contractes for gaine,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> but of relieving the poore; but he ſpeaketh of giving, and lending, which are <hi>contractus gratuiti, free contractes,</hi> or elſe the nature of them is marred: which two kindes of communicating goods, <hi>giving,</hi> and <hi>lending,</hi> are not onely allowed by God, as the contractes of <hi>buying, ſelling, ſetting,</hi> and <hi>hiring,</hi> and ſuch like are, but alſo are ſtraightly and ſeverely commaunded by God toward the poore and needy, having ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny threatnings menazed, if they be neglected, and many goodly promiſes annexed, if they be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed according to Gods commaundement, and therefore our Saviour would have them exerciſed, &amp; practized moſt freely, even without all hope of any recompence. But it is not true, that he ſpeaketh there onely of <hi>relieving the poore:</hi> for he ſpeaketh in the ſame verſe <hi>of loving one another,</hi> and of <hi>doing good one to another:</hi> which duties are not reſtrained onely to the relieving of the poore; neither doth any ſuch thing appeare in the 30. verſe. Whereas he ſpeaketh of giving them that aske, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:6252:44"/>
indeed is of the poore: ſo he ioyneth wthi it, <hi>and from him that taketh away thy goods from thee, aske them not againe,</hi> which is more likely to be done of other, than the poore, neither doth it touch the relieving of the poore.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Defendor.</note>
                  <hi>Secondly, for that this, which is to be done, Christ commaundeth to be done even to our enimies. Now there is no reaſon, or law of God that I ſhould lend my money to mine enimie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note>Firſt, the words of the text have no ſuch neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of lending to our enimies; for <hi>enimies</hi> have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to <hi>love,</hi> and therefore doe not love: but len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hath relation to ſuch as are not able to lend againe. Yet by conſequence it will follow from the text, that we muſt lend to our enimies; for we are commaunded there to doe aſ-much, that is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>to doe good, verſe</hi> 27. <hi>&amp;</hi> 35. yea to doe more a great deale than lending, that is, <hi>to love.</hi> For it is an eaſier thing to lend to an enimie, than to love him. And there is great reaſon that we ſhould lend to our very enimies, becauſe God did more than lend to us being more his enimies. But I pray you how doth his concluſion follow hence? <hi>That which he forbiddeth to be done, he commaundeth to be done to an enimie; Ergo, This place maketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt uſurie.</hi> I underſtand neither the ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent, nor the conſequence: that which is forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to be done is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to hope for the like:</hi> doth he commaund this, that is, <hi>to hope for the like</hi> of our enimies? This I underſtand not: but this I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand out of this place, as he expoundeth it: It is
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:6252:44"/>
not lawfull to hope for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the like,</hi> of our eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to whom we lend: <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is a great deale leſſe lawfull to take uſurie of our friends, and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly, for that I am commanded to lend him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Defendor.</note> 
                  <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I were in apparant danger, or rather manifeſt to loſe all, even the Principall: for the Greeke word ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth to looke for nothing of that thou lendeſt; which is not onely proved out of the nature of the word, but alſo out of the circumſtances of the place: for</hi> verſe 34. <hi>he teacheth that one ſinner lendeth to another to receive like, or aſmuch againe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What the Greeke word ſignifieth,<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> and what the circumſtances of the place beare, you have heard better reaſons before, than this Defendors bare word: and therefore I ſay no more, till I ſee more. But to his conſequence: Doth this place make nothing againſt uſurie, becauſe, you are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to <hi>lend</hi> franckly, &amp; freely without hoping, or looking for the principal againe? I think nothing maketh more againſt it:<note n="a" place="margin">If our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour muſt be holpen even without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect had of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Principall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: much more are uſurie compactes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, Beza in Luc. <hi>6.35.</hi>
                  </note> For much leſſe may you compact for certaine gaine above the Principall. The ſpeech of our Saviour Chriſt in this place is indefinite, and in the other member, which is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to it, and more than it, it is univerſall <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>to every one that asketh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To make ſome ſhew, that this place maketh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt uſury: he taketh upon him to anſwere two objections, which he imagineth may be made here.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If happely you ſay,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Defendor.</note> 
                  <hi>we muſt lend to the poore often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:6252:45"/>
without hope of recompence, yea, with hazard of the Principall: Ergo, we may not lend to the rich, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> recompence may be looked for again:</hi> non ſequitur. <hi>Christ co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth us to call the poore to our table, which cannot call us againe, Ergo, we may not invite our rich friends, which can invite us againe:</hi> non ſequitur.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note>And to conclude, <hi>Ergo,</hi> we may lend to the rich upon uſurie, <hi>Minùs ſequitur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Defendor.</note>
                  <hi>If you ſay, if he meant of relieving the poore, he would rather have ſpoken of giving, then of lending.</hi> I <hi>anſwere, that there is oftentimes more charitie ſhewed to a poore man in lending him ſomewhat, than in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving: for there are many poore, which being aſhamed to begge, and receive an almes, would yet willingly bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a peece of money, with mind to repay it, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note>Grant this (for God commandeth lending to the poore, as well as giving, and they are both ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie neceſſarie and beneficiall to the poore, in their ſeverall places) yet will it not follow, that it is anie charitie to take uſurie,<note place="margin">Baſil. hom. in uſurer.</note> or reliefe to pay uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, for that which is lent to poore, or rich. <hi>Baſil</hi> adviſing them that were unable to live, unleſſe they tooke upon uſurie, rather to begge; and they objecting that they were aſhamed to begge; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth, that it is more ſhame<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> to take upon uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and deceive: <hi>for</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>any thing is more</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable than to take upon uſurie.</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Plut. de non foen.</note> And <hi>Plutarke</hi> having rekoned up many waies and trades for men to live by, concludeth, that of all thoſe, none is ſo ſervile or ſhamefull, as to heare this voice of the Uſurer, <hi>Pay that thou owest.</hi> And whereas many object, that
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:6252:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
they cannot live without taking upon uſurie: <hi>Baſil</hi> anſwereth, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>There are many deviſes for a man to live by, many occaſions:</hi> and <hi>Plutark, doſt thou not ſee, how many waies the land, and how many meanes the ſea doth offer thee to live by?</hi> And what kinde of charitie it is, and how much better than giving, to lend upon uſurie, <hi>Baſil</hi> ſheweth in theſe wordes, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a bad giving to both, to wit, the giver, and the receiver, bringing loſſe &amp; damage, to the ones goods, and to the others ſoule.</hi> For the further <hi>defence, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of uſurie,</hi> out of the new Teſtament he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth three arguments.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>The Apostles of our Saviour Chriſt in their ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie catalogues of ſinne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Defendor.</note> 
                  <hi>doe never once make any ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all mention of uſurie in all their writings, whereby gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth a ſtrong praeſumption of the lawfulneſſe thereof. For in all likelihood they would not have kept ſilence therein, if their predeceſſors the Prophets had laboured ſo much againſt it, as they are ſuppoſed to have done by ſuch as draw the testimonies above-ſaid to the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation thereof: ſpecially ſeeing it is well knowne that in the Romane Empire, under which they preached uſurie, and lone for money was much uſed, and that as lawfull, to the value of twelve in the hundreth. At the least</hi> James, Peeter, <hi>and</hi> John <hi>would not likely have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten it, which wrote particularly to the Jewes much given to that kind of gaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt I denie this conſequence:<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> There is no ſpeciall mention of the forbidding of it by name in
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:6252:46"/>
the new Teſtament: <hi>ergo</hi> it is lawfull: for there are many breaches of the Morall law, yea many groſſe ſinnes, which are not expreſly mentioned, and forbidden by name in the New Teſtament: as namely <hi>profaning of the Sabboth day: all the degrees of Inceſt ſave one; removing the neighbours marke: taking for pledge, or upon execution a poore mans onely weed; removing of land marks: Polygamie; gelouſie, &amp;c.</hi> 2. It is forbidden in the old: and the new gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth no inlargement to ſinne. 3. Neither is the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of uſurie of a poore man, that is in never ſo great diſtreſſe, forbidden by name in the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, and therefore by this argument it ſhould be alſo lawfull, contrarie to the aſſertion of <hi>M.C.</hi> who affirmeth it to be a breach of the morall law, and unlawfull. And yet by conſequence uſurie is ſufficiently forbidden in the new Teſtament, as the learned<note n="a" place="margin">Baſil. hom. ad uſur. Ambroſ. de To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>15.</hi> Hier. in Ezech. <hi>18.</hi> Conc. lat. p. <hi>16.</hi> Tit. de uſura. Theſes Wittenb. Melancthon. &amp;c.</note> Divines both of ancient time, and of lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ages doe acknowledge:<note n="b" place="margin">Nazi. de theol. l. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and thoſe things which are collected out of the Scripture, are as well, as thoſe things which are written in the Scripture,</hi> as <hi>Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zene</hi> ſaid, and they come under the ſecond mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his quadripartite diviſion there, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>which are in the Scripture, and yet are not na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med there.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now for his ſurmiſe of likelihood for the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of uſurie in the Romane Empier, he ſhould have ſhewed how <hi>it is ſo well knowne,</hi> elſe we ſhall hardly beleeve it, upon theſe inducements.<note n="c" place="margin">Appian. de bello Ciuili. l. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Appian</hi> affirmeth that the <hi>ancient Romanes abhorred uſurie,</hi> and accompted it as <hi>cheating, and conſening</hi> (as the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:6252:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Perſians judged it full of <hi>deceite, and lying) and as a naturall breeder of enmitie, and diſcord,</hi> as the often and horrible<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> Liu. dec. <hi>1.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> &amp; l. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> troubles of that ſtate, tumults, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rores, ſeceſſions, and ſeditions about uſurie doe teſtifie: which Uſurie grew, and was practized a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, as <hi>Appian</hi> there ſaith,<note place="margin">Appian. de bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo ciuili. l. <hi>1.</hi> &amp;c.</note> by evill cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, and corruption of the times; not by any law, for their lawes were ever againſt it, either to reſtraine it, when by means of the power of the Uſurers they could doe no more; or utterly to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſh and forbid it; and to puniſh the Uſurers.<note n="b" place="margin">Liui. dec. <hi>1.</hi> l. <hi>7.</hi> de unciario ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nore.</note> For in the yeere of Rome 398. <hi>M. Duellius, L. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenius</hi> got a law made, that the rate of Uſurie ſhould not exceede an ounce, that is, 8⅓ in the 100. which was the higheſt rate that they ſuffered by law unpuniſhed: and within ten yeeres after, it was brought to<note n="c" place="margin">Liu. ibid. ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Semiuneia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium.</note> halfe an ounce, that is, to 4⅙ in the 100. and all debts were foreſtald to be paid at foure payments in three yeeres: and in the yeere<note n="d" place="margin">Liu. ibid.</note> 411. the Aediles ſued divers uſurers upon that Plebiſcite, and had them<note n="e" place="margin">Iudicia triſtia.</note> cruelly puniſhed. But in the yeere<note n="f" place="margin">Liu. ibid. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine.</note> 413. <hi>L. Genitius</hi> got a Plebiſcite enac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted<note n="g" place="margin">Ne foenerare liceret.</note> 
                  <hi>that no uſurie ſhould be taken,</hi> as our late Noble King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt ordeined in his<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Anno</hi> 5. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 20.</note> ſtatute. Of this proceeding againſt <hi>uſurie</hi> from an ounce to nothing<note n="i" place="margin">Corn. Tac. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. lib. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Cornelius Tacitus,</hi> who lived neere the Apoſtles times, maketh mention. The puniſhment of Uſurers in that ſtate, was to forfeite<note n="k" place="margin">Cato de re ruſt. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> fourefold, whereas theft was puniſhed with reſtoring onely dubble, as <hi>Cato</hi> ſaith. The two<note n="l" place="margin">Liu. dec. <hi>1.</hi> l. <hi>10</hi>
                  </note> Ogulnies being Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diles in the yeere 457. indited divers Uſurers, and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:6252:47"/>
of that part of the forfeitures, which came to the common treaſurie, made diverſe great and memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable works, which you may ſee in <hi>Livie.</hi> Likewiſe<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in. dec. <hi>4.</hi> l. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>M. Tuccius,</hi> and <hi>P. Iunius Brutus,</hi> being Aediles in the yeere of Rome 502, made of the forfeitures of Uſurers, golden chariots which they dedicated to <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and twelue golden ſhieldes; and built a porch without the gate <hi>Trigemina:</hi> and the like ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere proceeding againſt uſurers was folowed after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward by other good magiſtrates of that ſtate. For<note n="b" place="margin">Appian. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lo ciuili. l. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Aſellius</hi> the Pretor puniſhed them ſeverely in the yeere 665: and a little before the time of Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles,<note n="c" place="margin">Cic. ad Attic. <hi>5.</hi> epiſt. <hi>20.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Tully</hi> had reſtrained it in Sicilie; <hi>I. Caeſar</hi> ſuppreſſed it generally by a law<note n="d" place="margin">Suet. in Iul. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſ. c. <hi>42.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that no uſury ſhould be taken, but the Principall onely paid:</hi> and<note n="e" place="margin">Plut. in Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llo.</note> 
                  <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cullus</hi> in Aſia (where the Apoſtles were moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant) had utterly abandoned it, fore-ſtalling the debts in ſuch ſort, that the Creditor ſhould receaue the fourth part of the debtors revenewes, till the Principall was paid, and if he exacted any uſurie he ſhould looſe both vſurie, and Principall; and ſo indeed was<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Plat. de leg. l. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Platoes</hi> law, which doubtleſſe <hi>Lucullus</hi> remembred, and ſpecially reſpected, being himſelf a great Academique, as<note n="g" place="margin">Plut. ibidem.</note> 
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> reportes him, and<note n="h" place="margin">Cic. quaeſt. Acad.</note> 
                  <hi>Tullie</hi> makes him in his Academique queſtions. Therefore it is unlikely that Uſurie was ſo uſed in the Romane Empire, as he pretends. And for his other ſurmiſe, that the Iewes were ſo much given to it; and therefore that the Apoſtles which wrote particularly to them would not have forgotten it; I thinke that he ſlaundereth the Iewes
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:6252:47"/>
of that time, which did not practize uſurie ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly, as he weeneth, but rather they offended in another kind, which S. <hi>Iames</hi> reprehended in them, namely, hoording up of money till it ruſted, and cankred: <hi>Your gold, and ſilver is cankred,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 5.3.</note> 
                  <hi>and the ruſt thereof, &amp;c.</hi> Now had theſe Iewes beene ſo much given to uſurie, as this Defendor would perſwade us; doubtleſſe the turning, and returning of their money, would have kept it from ruſting, and cank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. Moreover, if the Iewes did practize uſurie in the Apoſtles times, yet it was but unto Aliants, (for even at this day they will not in any wiſe take uſurie of their brethren) and that uſurie was law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and commaunded by <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 23.20.</note> 
                  <hi>To the Aliant thou ſhalt uſurie.</hi> With whoſe ordinances the Apoſtles were loth to be over-buſie, as appeareth by the fact of <hi>Paule,</hi> and the opinion of all the Apoſtles. <hi>Act.</hi> 21.20.21.</p>
               <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">Defendor.</note> 
                  <hi>Our Saviour Chriſt is ſo farre from condemning it, that he ſeemeth to give ſome allowance to it: for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving the ſervant which ſuffered his talent lye idle, he affirmeth, that he ſhould have delivered it to the bankers, that the Lord might have receaved his owne with increaſe. Whereby he doth ſpeake of that gaine, as of a lawfull uſe of money: and withall ſeemeth to note, that if a man have no other lawfull trade to occupie his money in; it were better for him to let it out to uſe, then to let it lye idle by him. For Parables, eſpecially of our Saviour Chriſt doe keepe a comelineſſe, and ſeemelineſſe of ſpeech, fit for the perſons, and the things, by whom, and of which they are ſpoken. This part of the Parable
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:6252:48"/>
being the ſpeech of a Maſter, which reſembleth the Sonne of God himſelfe, it is not like that our Saviour Christ would aſcribe ſuch a ſpeech unto him, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenteth his owne ſelfe, as ſhould cary a note of an evill, and unhoneſt thing. Neither can it ſerve for an anſwere, that he compareth his comming to the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine breaking of a thiefe into the houſe. For although theft be an unlawfull act, that wherein Christ his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming onely is compared, is not unlawfull, nor condemned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Exod. 22.6.</note>No? Is not a thieves privie breaking into a mans houſe in the night an act unlawfull? Then <hi>Moſes</hi> did ill to make the killing of ſuch a man a lawfull act, though he were taken but in breaking in, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he had ſtolen any thing, or done any harme. Our Saviour likewiſe ſetteth forth the carefulneſſe, and forecaſting, which Chriſtians ſhould have in compaſſing eternall life,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.</note> to a ſervant, which to maintaine his bodily life deceived his Maſter in his accompts, and ſaved ſomewhat to maintaine his life; and the ſervant is commended for his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in it in holy Scripture: doth our Saviour therein give any allowance to ſervants deceiving of their maſters in their accompts? and yet the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants very deceiving of his maſter in his accompts, is that wherein the care of Chriſtians is compared, to uſe the Defendors words. That which is ſet downe in the Parable is a thing of it ſelfe unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; but yet is often done by the men of <hi>the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of this world;</hi> and therein <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> and comelineſſe conſiſteth, and is obſerved: but that which is ſet forth, and repreſented by the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:6252:48"/>
Parable, is a thing lawfull, namely, the increaſe of ſpirituall graces in the Church to the glory of Chriſt, gotten by the profitable imployment of the giftes lent us of God. Thus much in defence of that anſwere. Yet that anſwere is not needfull to this argument: for that uſurie, which thoſe ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers uſed, was then a lawfull trade, and action: namely, for the Iewes to lend upon uſurie to the Aliantes, and to receive uſurie of them: being made lawfull in that caſe by Gods law, being yet then in force: and therefore lawfully practized by the Iewes upon the Aliantes at that time when our Saviour uttered this Parable: unleſſe he can proue that thoſe bankers tooke uſurie of their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the Iewes; which they abhorre to doe at this day.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>There is not any of the properties of true love recited</hi> 1. Cor. 13, <hi>contrarie to this uſurie.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Defendor.</note> 
                  <hi>For even that which ſeemeth moſt to ſtrike at it,</hi> Love ſeeketh not her owne, <hi>may dwell together with uſurie which is here propounded: conſidering that I am bound to love my brother no otherwiſe than my ſelfe: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not to ſeeke him, and his, but that withall I have regard to me, and mine: both which are performed, when uſurie is ſo handled, that both the lender, and the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ower have reaſonable gaine, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But uſurie can never be ſo handled that the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower may gaine by paying it:<note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> becauſe whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he payeth for uſurie, he payeth of his owne goods, and doth ſo much diminiſh his owne ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, as before hath beene ſhewed. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:6252:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
this propertie of love doth ſtrike uſurie dead, becauſe the Uſurer ſeeketh not onely his owne, and aſſureth it too; which love doth not; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſeeketh, and taketh that which is none of his owne, but another mans: which appeareth moſt evidently by the poſition of this Defendor in the next wordes almoſt, where he ſaith, <hi>that in ſome caſe the lender may with a good conſcience exact his Principall with increaſe, where the borrower hath gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned nothing.</hi> Here is the uſurers conſcience indeed. And howſoever ſome pretend that they looke but for part of the gaine; <hi>lucrum de lucro,</hi> not <hi>nummum de nummo</hi> as he ſaid before: yet when it commeth to the point, the borrower ſhall finde this to be their conſcience, that they will be ſure to have their Principall, and lone too; gaine he, or gaine he not; yea though he loſe by it too: as this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendor ſheweth not obſcurely in the next wordes. <hi>If the borrower be a man fallen in decay, the lender is bound in Chriſtian duetie not onely not to exact his gaine ſo covenanted, but even to forgive the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall if his eſtate will beare it.</hi> Here be two excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concurring together, without which the len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may exact his covenanted gaine, though the borrower looſe by it. Firſt, the borrower muſt be in decay; ſo that if he be not a decayed man, though he doe looſe by uſing their money, he muſt pay the uſurie. Secondly, the lenders ſtate muſt beare it. And this I doubt he will hardly be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that his eſtate will beare the looſing of his lone, for it is his living, he cannot ſpare it. For
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:6252:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
there is no kind of men that make themſelves more needy then the Uſurers doe. So then in the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding up, the Defendor hath acquainted us with the ſcantling of the Uſurers conſcience: and the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower may aſſure himſelfe to finde it broader, and worſe, pretend they what they will. But he miſcal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it when he calles it a <hi>good conſcience:</hi> for what conſcience is it, that an occupier ſhall bee a rich mans ſervant, to occupie his ſtocke for him, while he lyeth idely at home, or followeth his pleaſures: and by ſuch croſſes, as God layeth upon him, to looſe by it; and yet not onely to make his ſtocke good, but alſo to yeeld him profit, and gaine for it? Or what conſcience is it, that ſaving but the Principal, he ſhall pay all the Principall to the Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and beare himſelfe all the loſſe of his owne paines, induſtrie, and skill; as deere to him, and commonly a great deale dearer, than the money to the Uſurer? Nay, what conſcience is it, that a man borrowing money of another, and venturing the ſame together with his induſtrie, and labour, and time; and in the end by turning, and returning of it, gaine ſomewhat toward his maintenance: then the Uſurer ſhall come in, and take away the beſt part of his gaine; never venturing any thing in the action? And yet all this is <hi>good conſcience</hi> with Uſurers; as this Defendor confeſſeth: and if he denied it, our lamentable experience teſtifieth it too apparantly. But all men know, that it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to naturall and common equitie, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth equalitie in the actions and dealings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:6252:50"/>
man and man: not that the one have the eaſe and profit, and the other be at all the paine and perill; and the faithfull know, that it is againſt Gods will, who will not that one have eaſe, and other the burthen. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.3. Now in that he ſaid here <hi>that uſurie is not againſt the love of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour;</hi> perhaps he meaneth (as ſome other object) that the Uſurer doth, as he would be done unto: for, wanting money for his neede, he would gladly give ten in the hundred; and thankes too. But this is eaſily anſwered. Firſt, that rule of our Saviour Chriſt is not generall, but reſtrainable to that will of man, which is ruled by nature, and Gods law: otherwiſe many abſurdities would follow. The Magiſtrate being in the malefactors caſe would gladly be pardoned; <hi>Ergo,</hi> he muſt pardon the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactor. Some man could be content, that ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould lye with his wife, whom he cares not for himſelfe: <hi>Ergo,</hi> he may lye with another mans wife, whom he loveth better. Some deſperate fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low would be glad that another ſhould kill him, as <hi>Saul</hi> was: <hi>Ergo,</hi> he may kill another. Secondly; the Uſurers aſſumption is falſe, for he doth not will that abſolutely, or freely; but of force, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint; becauſe without paying after that rate, he cannot have it: mary abſolutely he would have it to ſerve his turne, and pay nothing, If Uſurers be ſo impudent as to deny, that they had rather in their neede and neceſſitie have money lent them freely, than upon uſurie, their owne practize doth bewray their will. I have had little converſment with them,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:6252:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>
or acquaintance with their doings, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi rend="sup">a</hi> he ſaid) &amp; yet I can name for neede halfe a doſen at the leaſt of my knowledge (<hi>&amp; ſi unum noris omnes noris: ken one ken all,</hi> as the Poet ſaid) that needing money upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, their owne being out at uſe, have borrowed of other, whom they thinke will take no uſurie, at the leaſt they will offer him none. And other I have knowne, and can prove, that not having in hand to pleaſure a ſure man, that would give good conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; have made meanes to borrow the ſumme of a friend, for the time, and taken the uſurie himſelfe, without allowing, or offering one penny of it to him whoſe the Principal was: &amp; one of theſe being in a ſort demaunded it, tooke it in ſuch dudgeon, that he was ſcarſe good friends with the demander afterwards. Trie it who will, and he ſhall hardly find one of a thouſand (that is <hi>Salomons</hi> oddes) that will pay uſurie himſelfe, though he lend never ſo much upon uſurie, if there be any likely meanes for him to get it without.</p>
               <p>Thus haſt thou gentle reader, my good will, and indeuour to maintaine the truth of God ſet downe in his word, againſt the common ſinne of uſurie: the haynouſneſſe, and horriblenes whereof, other men have ſet forth at large: of whom among ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny excellent writers, I ſpecially commend to thy reading, among the Philoſophers, <hi>Plutarch, de non foenerando:</hi> among the ancient Fathers S. <hi>Baſils</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily againſt Uſurers: among latter Divines, <hi>Chem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicius</hi> common place, <hi>de paupertate, c.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 6: among
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:6252:51"/>
the Civilians, our owne Doctor <hi>Wilſons</hi> diſcourſe upon Uſurie. I thought it enough for me here, to cleare the doctrine of our Church, from the cavils and ſophiſtications of this Uſurie-defendor, ſet forth in this Pamphlet; which I know doth much harme in our Church, and Common-wealth, in dazeling the eyes of many, and drawing them into this notorious breach of Gods law, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe are Chriſtianly minded, and have a care of their waies, and would be moſt loath for any gaine to runne into contempt of Gods law. And now they having here, as a briefe, and familiar, ſo I hope a ſufficient anſwere, ſhewing their errors without blazing, or blemiſhing their names; I humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech the Lord to open the eyes both of the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and Defendors of Uſurie, and alſo of all the practizers of the ſame, that they may ſee their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe under their fig-leaves, and behold the fouleneſſe of their ſinne, under theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and viſardes, and waigh the dangerouſneſſe of their eſtate; that they may in time repent, and ſo avoid the Lords dreadfull judgements, which never can be avoyded with the ſophiſticall cavilles, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourable gloſes of mans wit.</p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Eſay. 5.20.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Woe be to them that call evill good, ſetting darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for light, ſower for ſweete.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:6252:51"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
